Hello! Welcome back to Cucumber School
In the last lesson
we saw how easily incidental details
can creep into your scenarios
talked about why they're a problem
and showed you some techniques
for massaging them back out again
But as we push the details
out of our scenarios
we made the step definition code
more complicated
We promised to show you how to deal
with that extra complexity
and that's what we'll do in this episode
First though, let's look at how
we could have prevented the premium accounts
feature from getting into such a mess
in the first place
In lesson 1 we showed you an example
of the three amigos -
tester, developer, and product owner -
having a conversation about
a new user story
What's the purpose of this conversation?
In software projects, it's often the
unknown unknowns that can make the
biggest difference between
success and failure
In BDD we always try to assume we're
ignorant of some important information
and try to deliberately discover those
unknown unknowns as early as possible
so they don't surprise us later on
That's what the three amigos is all about
Nobody likes long meetings so we've
developed a simple framework
for this conversation that
keeps it quick and effective
We call this Example Mapping
You'll need a multicoloured pack of index
cards and some pens
We use the different coloured cards to
represent the different kinds of
information that arise in the conversation
We can start with the easy stuff:
Take a yellow card
and write down the name of the story
Now do we already know any rules or
acceptance criteria about this story?
Write each rule down on a blue card
They look pretty straightforward but let's
explore them a bit
by coming up with some examples
Darren the developer comes up with a simple scenario to check he understands
the basics of the 'buy' rule:
I start with ten credits
I shout 'buy my muffins'
and then 'I want to buy some socks'
and then I have zero credits, correct?
Yes, says Paula
Darren writes example upon a green card
and places it underneath the rule
that it illustrates
Tammy the tester chimes in:
How about the one where you shout a word
that contains 'buy' like 'buyer' for example?
If you were to shout 'I need a buyer for my
house' would that lose credits too?
Paula thinks about this for a minute
and decides that no
only the whole word buy counts
They've discovered a new rule!
They write that up on the rule card and
place the example card underneath it
Darren asks:
How do users get these credits?
Are we building that functionality
as part of the story?
Paula tells him that's part of another story
and they can assume the user already
can purchase credits
They write that down as a rule too
This isn't a behaviour rule
it's a rule about the scope of the story
but it's still useful to write it down
since we've agreed on it
but it won't need any examples
Still focussed on the 'buy' rule, Tammy asks:
What if they run out of credit?
Say you start with 10 credits
and shout 'buy' three times
What's the outcome?
Paula looks puzzled
I don't know, she says
I'll need to give that some thought
Darren takes a red card and writes this up
as a question
They apply the same technique to the other
rule about long messages and pretty soon
the table is covered in cards reflecting
the rules, examples, and questions
that have come up in their conversation
Now they have a picture in front of them
that reflects back what they know
and still don't know about this story
The apparent purpose of the three amigos
is to take a user story together with its
acceptance criteria or business rules and produce examples that illustrate the behaviour
Many people think they need to produce
formal Gherkin scenarios
from their three amigos conversations
but in our experience
that's only occasionally necessary
In fact, it can often slow the
discussion down
As you've just seen, an example mapping
session should go right across
the breadth of the story, trying to get a
complete picture of the behaviour
Each time you come up with an example
try to understand what the underlying rules are
If you discover a scenario that
doesn't fit your rules
you'll need to reconsider your rules
In this way the acceptance criteria for the story
are refined by the group
Although there's no doubt of the
power of examples for exploring
and talking through requirements
it's the rules that will go into the code
If you understand the rules
you'll be able  to build an elegant solution
Sometimes you'll come across questions
that nobody in the group can answer
Instead of getting stuck trying to come up
with an answer
just write down the question
Congratulations!
You've just turned an unknown unknown
into a known unknown
That's progress
Deciding what a story is not -
and maximizing the amount of work not done
is one of the most useful things you
can do in a three amigos session
Small stories are the secret of a
successful agile team
By talking through the details
of the behaviour
we ensure that the tester
developer and product owner
are all in agreement about
what needs to be built
A shared understanding emerges
between them
They also learn a little more about
one another's perspective
Some people tell us the three amigos has
helped to build empathy within their team!
With this goal in mind
make sure the three amigos
isn't just a rubber stamping exercise
where one person does all the talking
Notice how in our example everyone
in the group was asking questions
and writing new cards?
One last tip is to run your three amigo
sessions inside a time box
When you're practiced at it you should be able to
analyze a story within 25 minutes
If you can't, it's either too big or
you don't understand it well enough yet
Either way it's not ready to play
At the end of the 25 minutes you can
check whether everyone thinks the story
is ready to start work on
If lots of questions remain it will be risky
to start work, but people might be
comfortable taking on a story with only a
few minor questions to clear up
Check this with a quick thumb-vote
When we build software we're always
working across two domains
There's the problem domain, where our customers and business stakeholders live
and there's a solution domain
where we solve those business problems
using technology
Each domain has its own jargon
its own dialect
That's fine: specialized language helps
domain experts to communicate
Often though, this jargon can prevent us
from understanding one another across
the two domains
As BDD practitioners
we're focussed on trying to grow
this area in the middle
where we have a common or ubiquitous language
We know that the bigger the
shared vocabulary is
the quicker the team can communicate ideas
between the business and technology
facing sides of the team
We've also heard it said
that if you model the problem well enough
the solution will take care of itself
Certainly we believe that the
better understanding you have of
the problem domain
the better a solution you can build
That's why Cucumber is so powerful
because it helps you to stay rooted
in a problem domain
So where do your feature files sit
on this diagram?
Well, we hope they sit right in
the middle here and act as
the place where the problem and solution
domains come together
Someone from either domain should be
able to read a feature file
and it will make sense to them
And how about step definitions?
Step definitions are right on the boundary
here
translating between the problem domain language
we use in our Gherkin scenarios
and the concrete actions we take in code
to pull and poke at our solution
We want to prevent solution domain
concepts and language
from leaking into our gherkin scenarios
so that we keep them readable
As we saw in the last lesson when we
remove details from scenarios
we trade off for increased complexity in
our step definitions
So how do we manage this complexity?
A mature Cucumber test suite will have a
layer of support code sitting between
the step definitions and the system being
automated
This layer of support code
literally supports the step definitions
by providing an API for automating
your application
We can extract this API
from our step definitions
Let's pick up the Shouty code base
and show you what we mean
We need a new directory to contain our
support code
The conventional place to put it is here in a support directory underneath features
There's a special file in support
that Cucumber always loads first called
E N V or env.rb
You can use this to boot up the system
that you're testing
In this case, our system is just
a domain model, but we can load it here
instead of from the step definitions
The most obvious duplication in the
step definition code is for
Sean shouting a message
Let's imagine we had
a helper method like this instead
Wouldn't that be neater?
Every time Cucumber runs a scenario
it creates a new object called the world
Each step definition runs inside this
world object
almost as though it were a method
We can extend the methods available
on the world
by first defining them on a ruby module then
registering that module with Cucumber
We'll create a new file in the support directory
to contain our extensions to the world
Now, we define a module and tell Cucumber
to make it part of the world
Finally, we define our new helper method
on this module
and paste in the code from the step definition
Now let's run Cucumber
to check everything's still working
Good
Now we can use that new method
everywhere...
and check we haven't broken anything...
done!
Notice that the helper method we extracted
still uses those instance variables
people and messages_shouted_by
This works because the helper methods
are mixed into the same world object
as the step definitions so they can all
see these instance variables
However, we don't like sharing state
across the support API boundary like this
Things can get complicated quickly when
you have code spread all over your
step definitions and support directory
that's depending on these instance variables
It's better to push the state behind
the support API
Let's start with the hash of people
We'll define a new method on the world
that returns the people instance variable
initializing it with an empty hash if it's
never been accessed before
Now we can use this method everywhere
in the step definitions
and we no longer need to initialize it
in this before hook
Let's run Cucumber to check
we haven't broken anything
Good
Now we can do exactly the same thing
with messages_shouted_by
First, create the helper method, then
replace the calls from the step definitions
Now we can remove this
before hook altogether
And finally, run Cucumber
to check we're still green
We could continue to move code
from our step definitions
into the support code like this
For example,
we could write a support method for
generating messages of a certain length
Ideally each step definition should only
contain one or two lines that delegate
to your support code
When you follow this principle your
step definitions become a
translation layer from plain language
into code
By keeping the vocabulary consistent
as you move across the
problem-solution boundary
you start to allow the scenarios
to drive the design of your domain model
This is what we call modeling by example
In this way we create our API for
automating our application
As this API grows, it becomes
easier and easier to write new step definitions
because the actions you need to take are
already defined on the API
It might seem like over engineering
on our little Shouty application but
you'll be surprised how quickly
these test suites grow
Taking time to stamp out complexity early
and organise your code to
create a good support API is a great
investment for the future
In a future lesson, we'll show you how
a well-crafted automation API like this
lets you plug your scenarios into the
system at different levels
such as a web front-end
The other investment we showed you about
in this episode is the
three amigos conversation
Taking a little time to explore your
user story in a collaborative setting
before you start to code it
can save an enormous amount of
time and effort down the line
Finding mistaken assumptions and
misunderstandings costs almost nothing
when you're just pushing
pieces of card around the table
As my grandma used to say
'A stitch in time saves nine'
It might feel like an overhead to have these
three amigos meetings for every story
but we think you'll be surprised
how much you can discover
from just that 25 minute conversation
Give it a try!
And I'll see you next time on
Cucumber School
Captions created by Jayson Smith for Cucumber Ltd.