Hello, and welcome back to
Cucumber School!
Last time we learned about two very
different kinds of loops
First, we use DataTables to loop over data
in your scenarios
Then we learned about TDD cycles
We saw how the outer loop of TDD
helps you build the right thing
while the inner loop helps you
build the thing right
In this lesson, we're going to teach you
all about how to configure Cucumber
When we start working on a new scenario
we often take a dive down
into the inner loop of TDD
where we use a unit testing tool
to drive out new classes or modify
the behaviour of existing ones
When our unit tests are green
and the new code is implemented
we return to the Cucumber scenarios
to verify whether we have made
overall progress or not
If we have lots of Cucumber scenarios
it can be distracting to run all of them
each time we do this
We often want to focus
on a single scenario
or perhaps just a couple
to get feedback on what
we're currently working on
There are several ways to do this in
Cucumber
Probably the easiest way is to
tell Cucumber to run only
a scenario with a particular name
The name option tells Cucumber to run
scenarios with a name matching
'Message is too long'
The value of this option is actually a
regular expression
so you can use your imagination her
to run more than one scenario
Another way to tell Cucumber to run a
specific scenario is to specify the
line number of the scenario within a
feature file
You can even specify multiple line
numbers for each file
to run more than one scenario
You can list several files and lines
together like this if you have
a specific set of scenarios
you want to run
When a scenario fails you'll notice that
Cucumber outputs the command
you can use to rerun that
particular scenario again
You can just copy Cucumber's output
and paste it into your command prompt
Narrowing down the set of scenarios
to run like this is called filtering
Cucumber has a third filtering mechanism
that uses tags
Tags start with an @ sign
We'll put a focus tag right here
above this scenario
Now we can run the scenarios tagged with focus
There should only be one
Yep
It's entirely up to you what you
name your tags
When we're working on a particular
area of the application
it's common to use a temporary tag
like this
We'll remove it before we check our code
into source control
Tags can be used for other purposes
as well
If you have lots of scenarios it can be
time-consuming to run them all every time
For example
you can tag a few of them with smoke
and run only those
before you check in code to source control
This will give you a certain level of
confidence that nothing is broken
without having to run every single one
If you're running Cucumber on a
CI, continuous integration, server as well
you could run all the scenarios there
detecting any regressions you might have
missed by only running the smoke tests
Tags give you a way to organise your
scenarios that
cuts across feature files
You can think of them like sticky labels
you might put into a book
to mark interesting pages
that you want to refer back to
Some teams also use tags to reference
external documents
For example, tickets in an
issue tracker or planning tool
Let's pretend we're using an issue tracker
while working on Shouty
and all the behaviour we built so far
is related to the issue number 11
We could tag the whole feature file
with the single line at the top
All the scenarios within that file
now inherit that tag
If you want to you can use more complex
tag expressions to select the scenarios
you want to run
For example
you could use a tag expression to exclude
all the scenarios tagged as @slow
Let's take a look at some of the
configuration options Cucumber offers
If we pass the help option to Cucumber
it will exit immediately
without running any scenarios
and print all the available options
along with some useful documentation
For example
you can see more details here about the
boolean expressions used for tag filtering
Let's take a closer look at the
format option
So far every time we've run Cucumber
it has printed the features back to us
in the console
Cucumber can report results
in other formats
and this is useful for generating reports
Let's try the HTML formatter
When we use the HTML formatter
we use --out to specify the file where
the report should be written
otherwise the HTML would be written
directly to the console
Let's try another one:
JSON
The JSON report outputs the results
to a single file
You can write your own script or program
to post-process this file
to generate your own report
There's also a progress formatter which
just prints out a single character
for each step
The JUNIT formatter outputs results
in an XML format which
many continuous integration servers
will turn into a nice report
We can specify multiple formatters
like this
The one without a --out
will be written to the console
One of these formatter plug-ins
is rather special -
the rerun formatter
Before we try it out, let's make
one of our scenarios fail
Right
Now we choose the rerun formatter
and send the output to a file called
rerun.txt
Let's look at what's in that rerun.txt file
It's a list of the scenarios that failed
and the format looks familiar doesn't it?
It's using the line number filtering format
we showed you earlier
This is really useful when you have
a few failing scenarios
and you want to rerun only
the ones that failed
We can pass this to Cucumber the
next time we run it
simply by prepending an @ sign
in front of the path
This is a big time saver when you're
in the middle of a refactoring
where you've broken a few scenarios
and you're working yourself back to green
The dry run option will quickly tell you
whether any of your steps are undefined
but it won't try to run any of them
It can be useful to get quick feedback
if you change the wording in your steps
The strict option affects the
exit status of Cucumber
To see how it works
let's add an undefined step
Let's first run it without strict
That last command tells us that
Cucumber didn't fail
it exited with an exit status of zero
which means success
Now, let's run it with strict
Ah, this time the exit status was one
indicating that Cucumber failed
Why is this interesting?
Well, if you run Cucumber on a
continuous integration server
it will fail the build if there are
undefined or pending steps
That's pretty handy!
Cucumber is first and
foremost a tool that facilitates a
common understanding between
people on a project
Imagine our customers were cats
We could write our features in English
but the cats would obviously not
understand that
We all know that cats speak
LOLCAT not English
so our feature would have to look like this
in order for cats to understand
We tell Cucumber what language to use
by adding a language comment
at the top of the file
Cucumber supports over 60 different
spoken languages thanks to contributions
from people and cats all over the world
You can get a list of all the supported
languages with - - i18n help
To see the translation of Gherkin
keywords for a particular language
just replace help with the language code
For example --i18n hi for Hindi
It would be tedious if you had to write out
these configuration options
every time you run Cucumber
To make this easier, you can write
the options in a file that Cucumber will pick up
You can use the cucumber.yml file
to define one or more profiles
that describe a set of
configuration options for Cucumber
For example
we can define a @dev profile that runs
only the @focus scenarios
and uses the progress formatter
Then we use the --profile option to choose
this profile when running Cucumber
To change the default behaviour of Cucumber
change the default profile
Let's make Cucumber strict by default
It's common for teams to have
a number of profiles defined
usually for the different environments
where Cucumber runs
You can have a CI profile that
behaves differently
to the ones you use on your dev machines
for example
To make Cucumber really useful
to your team
it's good to spend time learning the
details of how to configure it
In this lesson we gave you a tour of almost all of
Cucumber's configuration options
You learned how to filter scenarios
by name, line number, or tag
You learned how to format Cucumber's output
and you learned how to write your scenarios
in different spoken languages
You also learned how to set up
different configurations
for use by your whole team
That's all for this lesson of Cucumber School
See you next time!
Captions created by Jayson Smith for Cucumber Ltd.