Hello! Welcome back to Cucumber School
In the last lesson
we saw how easily incidental details
can creep into your scenarios
talked about why they're a problem
and showed you some techniques
for massaging them back out again
But as we push the details
out of our scenarios
we made the step definition code
more complicated
We promised to show you how to deal
with that extra complexity
and that's what we'll do in this episode
First though, let's look at how
we could have prevented the premium accounts
feature from getting into such a mess
in the first place
In lesson 1 we showed you an example
of the three amigos -
tester, developer, and product owner -
having a conversation about
a new user story
What's the purpose of this conversation?
In software projects, it's often the
unknown unknowns that can make the
biggest difference between
success and failure
In BDD we always try to assume we're
ignorant of some important information
and try to deliberately discover those
unknown unknowns as early as possible
so they don't surprise us later on
That's what the three amigos is all about
Nobody likes long meetings so we've
developed a simple framework
for this conversation that
keeps it quick and effective
We call this Example Mapping
You'll need a multicoloured pack of index
cards and some pens
We use the different coloured cards to
represent the different kinds of
information that arise in the conversation
We can start with the easy stuff:
Take a yellow card
and write down the name of the story
Now do we already know any rules or
acceptance criteria about this story?
Write each rule down on a blue card
They look pretty straightforward but let's
explore them a bit
by coming up with some examples
Darren the developer comes up with a
simple scenario to check he understands
the basics of the 'buy' rule:
I start with ten credits
I shout 'buy my muffins'
and then 'I want to buy some socks'
and then I have zero credits, correct?
Yes, says Paula
Darren writes example upon a green card
and places it underneath the rule
that it illustrates
Tammy the tester chimes in:
How about the one where you shout a word
that contains 'buy' like 'buyer' for example?
If you were to shout 'I need a buyer for my
house' would that lose credits too?
Paula thinks about this for a minute
and decides that no
only the whole word buy counts
They've discovered a new rule!
They write that up on the rule card and
place the example card underneath it
Darren asks:
How do users get these credits?
Are we building that functionality
as part of the story?
Paula tells him that's part of another story
and they can assume the user already
can purchase credits
They write that down as a rule too
This isn't a behaviour rule
it's a rule about the scope of the story
but it's still useful to write it down
since we've agreed on it
but it won't need any examples
Still focussed on the 'buy' rule, Tammy asks:
What if they run out of credit?
Say you start with 10 credits
and shout 'buy' three times
What's the outcome?
Paula looks puzzled
I don't know, she says
I'll need to give that some thought
Darren takes a red card and writes this up
as a question
They apply the same technique to the other
rule about long messages and pretty soon
the table is covered in cards reflecting
the rules, examples, and questions
that have come up in their conversation
Now they have a picture in front of them
that reflects back what they know
and still don't know about this story
The apparent purpose of the three amigos
is to take a user story together with its
acceptance criteria or business rules
and produce examples that
illustrate the behaviour
Many people think they need to produce
formal Gherkin scenarios
from their three amigos conversations
but in our experience
that's only occasionally necessary
In fact, it can often slow the
discussion down
As you've just seen, an example mapping
session should go right across
the breadth of the story, trying to get a
complete picture of the behaviour
Each time you come up with an example
try to understand what the underlying rules are
If you discover a scenario that
doesn't fit your rules
you'll need to reconsider your rules
In this way the acceptance criteria for the story
are refined by the group
Although there's no doubt of the
power of examples for exploring
and talking through requirements
it's the rules that will go into the code
If you understand the rules
you'll be able  to build an elegant solution
Sometimes you'll come across questions
that nobody in the group can answer
Instead of getting stuck trying to come up
with an answer
just write down the question
Congratulations!
You've just turned an unknown unknown
into a known unknown
That's progress
Deciding what a story is not -
and maximizing the amount of work not done
is one of the most useful things you
can do in a three amigos session
Small stories are the secret of a
successful agile team
By talking through the details
of the behaviour
we ensure that the tester
developer and product owner
are all in agreement about
what needs to be built
A shared understanding emerges
between them
They also learn a little more about
one another's perspective
Some people tell us the three amigos has
helped to build empathy within their team!
With this goal in mind
make sure the three amigos
isn't just a rubber stamping exercise
where one person does all the talking
Notice how in our example everyone
in the group was asking questions
and writing new cards?
One last tip is to run your three amigo
sessions inside a time box
When you're practiced at it you should be able to
analyze a story within 25 minutes
If you can't, it's either too big or
you don't understand it well enough yet
Either way it's not ready to play
At the end of the 25 minutes you can
check whether everyone thinks the story
is ready to start work on
If lots of questions remain it will be risky
to start work, but people might be
comfortable taking on a story with only a
few minor questions to clear up
Check this with a quick thumb-vote
When we build software we're always
working across two domains
There's the problem domain, where our customers and business stakeholders live
and there's a solution domain
where we solve those business problems
using technology
Each domain has its own jargon
its own dialect
That's fine: specialized language helps
domain experts to communicate
Often though, this jargon can prevent us
from understanding one another across
the two domains
As BDD practitioners
we're focussed on trying to grow
this area in the middle
where we have a common or ubiquitous language
We know that the bigger the
shared vocabulary is
the quicker the team can communicate ideas
between the business and technology
facing sides of the team
We've also heard it said
that if you model the problem well enough
the solution will take care of itself
Certainly we believe that the
better understanding you have of
the problem domain
the better a solution you can build
That's why Cucumber is so powerful
because it helps you to stay rooted
in a problem domain
So where do your feature files sit
on this diagram?
Well, we hope they sit right in
the middle here and act as
the place where the problem and solution
domains come together
Someone from either domain should be
able to read a feature file
and it will make sense to them
And how about step definitions?
Step definitions are right on the boundary
here
translating between the problem domain language
we use in our Gherkin scenarios
and the concrete actions we take in code
to pull and poke at our solution
We want to prevent solution domain
concepts and language
from leaking into our gherkin scenarios
so that we keep them readable
As we saw in the last lesson when we
remove details from scenarios
we trade off for increased complexity in
our step definitions
So how do we manage this complexity?
A mature Cucumber test suite will have a
layer of support code sitting between
the step definitions and the system being
automated
This layer of support code
literally supports the step definitions
by providing an API for automating
your application
We can extract this API
from our step definitions
Let's pick up the Shouty code base
and show you what we mean
We need a new class to contain
our support code
Let's create a class called ShoutSupport
in the same package as our step definitions
We already have a shout method
in our step definition class
Let's cut that method and paste it
into the support class
We'll make it public
and rename it to seanShout
We also need the two maps:
people and messagesShoutedBy
Let's cut and paste those as well
We'll instantiate these maps where they're declared
and declare them public and final
Now that we have a new ShoutSupport class
let's put it to use in our step definitions
We'll declare a constructor to pass it in
store the reference in a shoutSupport field
and call this method everywhere
we used to call shout
Since our maps are now moved
we need to access these from the
shoutSupport object as well
Cucumber now fails with an error
complaining that the Stepdefs class
doesn't have an empty constructor
You may not have given it much thought
but Cucumber creates a new instance of
every class with step definitions
before every scenario
Cucumber knows how to instantiate classes
with empty constructors
but when the classes expect
dependencies to be passed in
Cucumber needs to delegate
the instantiation of objects
to a dependency injection container
Cucumber supports half a dozen
dependency injection containers
Let's pick a simple one that
doesn't require any configuration:
PicoContainer
Now that Cucumber's successfully
instantiate objects
let's finish our refactoring
We'll know we're done when
all the scenarios are green again
We could continue to move
code from our step definitions
into the support code like this
For example
we could write a support method for
generating messages of a certain length
Ideally, each step definition should only
contain one or two lines that delegate
to your support code
When you follow this principle
your step definitions become
a translation layer
from plain language into code
By keeping the vocabulary consistent
as you move across the problem-solution boundary
you start to allow the scenarios
to drive the design of your domain model
This is what we call modeling by example
In this way we create our API for automating our application
As this API grows
it becomes easier and easier
to write new step definitions
because the actions you need to take
are already defined on the API
It might seem like over engineering
on our little Shouty application
but you'll be surprised how quickly
these test Suites grow
Taking time to stamp out complexity early
and organise your code
to create a good support API
is a great investment for the future
In a future lesson
we'll show you how a
well-crafted automation API like this
lets you plug your scenarios into
the system at different levels
such as a web front-end
The other investment we showed you
about in this episode is the
three amigos conversation
Taking a little time to explore your user story
in a collaborative setting
before you start to code it
can save an enormous amount of
time and effort down the line
Finding mistaken assumptions
and misunderstandings
costs almost nothing when you're just
pushing pieces of card around the table
As my grandma used to say
'A stitch in time saves nine'
It might feel like an overhead to have these
three amigos meetings for every story
but we think you'll be surprised
how much you can discover from just
that 25 minute conversation
Give it a try!
And I'll see you next time on
Cucumber School
Captions created by Jayson Smith for Cucumber Ltd.