Hello, and welcome back to Cucumber School!
Last time we talked about the importance of
having readable scenarios
and you learned some new skills with
regular expressions to help you achieve that goal
Those skills will give you the confidence
to write scenarios exactly the way you want
knowing you’ll be able to match the Gherkin steps
easily from your step definition code
We emphasise readability
because from our experience
writing Gherkin scenarios
is a software design activity
Cucumber was created
to bridge the communication gap
between business domain experts
and development teams
When you collaborate with domain experts
to describe behaviour in Gherkin
you’re expressing the group’s shared understanding
of the problem you need to solve
The words you use in your scenarios
can have a deep impact on the way
the software is designed
as we’ll see in later episodes
The more fluent you become in writing Gherkin
the more useful a tool it becomes
to help you facilitate this communication
Keeping your scenarios readable means
you can get feedback at any time
about whether you’re building the right thing
Over time, your features become
living documentation about your system
We can’t emphasise enough
how important it is to see your scenarios
as more than just tests
Maintaining a living document works both ways:
you’ll drive your solution design
from your scenarios
but you may also have to update your Gherkin
to reflect the things you learn
as you build the solution
This dance back and forth between features
and solution code is what BDD is all about
Today, we’ll learn about
feature descriptions, the Background keyword
and about keeping scenarios and code up-to-date
with your current understanding of the project
First, let’s catch up with
what’s been happening on the Shouty project
While we were away, the developers of Shouty
have been busy working on the code
Let’s have a look at what they’ve been up to
We’ll start out by running Cucumber
Great!
It looks like both these scenarios
are working now -
both the different messages
that Sean shouts are being heard by Lucy
Let’s dig into the code
and see how these steps have been automated
In the step definition layer
we can see that a new class has been defined
the Network
We’re creating an instance of the network here
Then we pass that network instance to each
of the Person instances we create here
So both instances of Person depend on
the same instance of network
The Network is what allows people
to send messages to one another
There’s also a new folder here, spec
This contains unit tests for the classes
in our domain model
There’s a network spec and a person spec
Unit tests are fine-grained tests that define the
precise behaviour of each of these classes
We’ll talk more about this in a future lesson
but feel free to have a poke around
in there in the meantime
You can use the `rspec` command to run the tests
RSpec does a lovely job of
formatting the output to tell us
the responsibilities of each of these objects
The first thing I notice coming back to the code
is that the feature file is still talking about
the distance between Lucy and Sean
but we haven’t actually implemented
any behaviour around that yet
This happens to us all the time -
we have an idea for a new feature
but then we find the problem is
too complex to solve all at once
so we break it down into simpler steps
If we’re not careful, little bits of that
original idea can be left around like clutter
in the scenarios and in the code
That clutter can get in the way
especially if plans change
We’re definitely going to develop this behaviour
but we’ve decided to defer it to our next iteration
Our current solution is just focussed
on broadcasting messages between
the people on the network
Let’s clean up the feature to
reflect that current understanding
After the feature keyword, we have space
in a Gherkin document
to write any arbitrary text that we like
We call this the feature’s description
This is a great place to write up any notes
or other details that
can’t easily be expressed in examples
You might have links to
wiki pages or issue trackers
or to wireframes for example
You can put anything you like in here, as long
as you don’t mention the magic word scenario
A common thing to do here for a new feature
is write out the user story we’re working on
This is a good place to start, so let’s do that
Good
Now we have an overarching story to guide us as we go
Something we really like to put into the description
are the acceptance criteria or
business rules we’re trying to implement
In this case, we can explain that
for the time being, we’re broadcasting to
all users, irrespective of distance
Because we know we’ll need to
filter by proximity - later -
we can also write a TODO list here so it’s clear
that we do intend to get to that soon
Changing the description doesn’t change anything
about how Cucumber will run this feature
It just helps the human beings reading this document
to understand more of what you understand
about the system you’re building
The step 'Given Lucy is 15m from Sean' is misleading
since the distance between the two people
is not yet relevant in our current model
We have this code here
a move_to method on Person
that’s being called from the step definition
but doesn’t actually do anything
Let’s simplify this code to do just what
it needs to do right now, and no more
We can start from the scenario by
changing this single step
to express what’s actually going on
We’ll work on one scenario at a time, and update
the other one once we’re happy with this one
There!
Now we have two steps, each creating a person
Notice we’re starting to reveal some more of
our domain language here:
we’ve introduced the words person and name
Person is already a part of our domain language
so it’s nice to have that revealed
in the language of the scenario
Name may well become an attribute
of our person soon
so it’s also useful to have that surfaced so
we can get feedback about it from the team
One thing we’ve lost by doing this
is the idea that, eventually
the two people will need to be close to each other
for the message to be transmitted
We definitely wouldn’t remove
detail like that unilaterally
without discussing it with the other people
who were in the three amigos meeting with us
when the example was written
In this case, as well as adding it
to the TODO list above
we’ve decided to update the names of
the existing scenarios
and write a couple of new empty scenarios
to remind us to implement that behaviour later
Now the scenario names make sense
and we’ve got a reminder of
future scenarios we’ll need to implement
Let's press on
We can run Cucumber to generate
new step definition snippets for the new steps...
and paste them into our steps file
Now to implement these two separate steps
we have a bit of a problem
We need the same instance of Network
available in both
We could just assume that the Lucy step
will always run first and create it there
but that seems fragile
If someone wrote a new scenario
that didn’t create people in the right order
they’d end up with no Network instance
and weird bugs
We want our steps to be as independent as possible
so they can be easily composed into new scenarios
Luckily Cucumber has a feature called hooks
that allows us to do exactly what we want here
We need an instance of Network in every scenario
so we can run a Before Hook
that creates one before
every scenario starts, like this
Now we can use that Network instance
as we create Lucy and Sean in these two new steps
It should be working again now.
Let’s run cucumber to check
Good
Let’s do the same with the other scenario
OK, so we’ve cleaned things up a bit
to bring the scenarios, the code
and our current understanding
of the problem all into sync
What’s nice to see is how well
those new steps that create Lucy and Sean
match the code inside the step definition
When step definitions have to make a big leap
to translate between our plain-language
description of the domain
in the Gherkin scenario, and the code
that’s usually a sign that something is wrong
We like to see step definitions that are only
one or two lines long
because that usually indicates
our scenarios are doing a good job
of reflecting the domain model
in the code and vice-versa
One problem that we still have with these scenarios
is that we’re very fixed to only being able
to use these two characters, Lucy and Sean
If we want to introduce anyone else
into the scenario
we’re going to be creating
quite a lot of duplicate code
In fact
the two steps for creating
Lucy and Sean are almost identical
apart from those instance variables
Now on a real project
we wouldn’t bother about
such a tiny amount of duplication
at this early stage...
but this isn’t a real project!
Let’s play with the skills we learned
last week to make a single step definition
that can create Lucy or Sean
The first problem we’ll need to tackle
is those hard-coded instance variable names
We can use Ruby’s hash to store
all the people involved in the scenario
in a single instance variable
Let’s try replacing Lucy first
We’ll start by creating a new hash
in the before hook, like this
Now we can story Lucy in a key in that hash
We’ll use her name as the key
hard-coding it for now
Finally, where we check Lucy’s messages heard
here in the assertion
we need to fetch her out of the hash
With that little refactoring done
we can now try and make this first step
generic for any name
Using your new found regular expression skills
from the last lesson
you’ll know that if we surround the word
Lucy here with a capture group
we’ll have the name passed into our
step definition as an argument, here
Now we can use that as the key in the hash
Finally, we can replace the hard-coded Lucy
in the pattern with \w+
meaning one or more word characters
A word in other words!
Now we have a totally generic step
If we try and run Cucumber now
we get an error about an ambiguous match
Our newly generic step definition
is now matching the step
'a person named Sean'
but so is the original one!
In bigger projects, this can be a real issue
so this warning is important
Let’s remove the old step definition
and fetch Sean from the hash, here
where he shouts his message
Great, we’re green again!
Let’s switch back to the feature
to show you one more technique
for improving the readability of your scenarios
When we have common context steps - the givens -
in all the scenarios in our feature
it can sometimes be useful to get those out of the way
We can literally move them into the background
using a background keyword, like this
As far as Cucumber is concerned
these scenarios haven’t changed
It will still create both Lucy and Sean
as the first things it does
when running each of these scenarios
But from a readability point of view
we can now see more clearly what’s important
and interesting about these two scenarios -
in this case, the message being shouted
Notice we just went straight into When steps
in our scenarios
That’s absolutely fine!
We still have a context for the scenario
but we’ve chosen to push it off into the background
Again, it’s debatable whether we’d bother
to use a Background yet on a real project
but this at least illustrates the technique
Hopefully, you’re already thinking about
how you can use it in your own code
To maintain trust in the BDD process,
it’s important to keep your features fresh
Even when you drive the development
from BDD scenarios
you’ll still learn lessons from the implementation
that might need to be
fed back into your Gherkin documentation
In this case, we discovered that
we could find a smaller slice of this story
and defer the business rule about proximity
until our next iteration
Splitting stories like this
is a powerful agile technique
and one that BDD can help you to master
Now we have a clean code base
and suite of scenarios that reflects
the current state of the system’s development
We’re ready to start the next iteration!
Captions created by Jayson Smith for Cucumber Ltd.