Hi there! Welcome back to Cucumber School
In the last lesson we took a break
from the code
to sharpen up your skills with
Cucumber's command-line interface
Now it's time to dive right back into the code
We're going to explore one of
the hottest topics that teams come across
when they start to get to grips with Cucumber and BDD:
how much detail to use in your scenarios
Many teams find
they can't easily agree on this
It can often seem like a matter of personal preference
It's true there are no right and wrong
answers but we're going to teach you
some principles that you can apply
to help you make better decisions
Once again, while we were away the
developers of Shouty have been busy
A new hotshot ninja rockstar
subcontractor Stevie
has built a new feature called
premium accounts
We don't know much about it yet
but our tester Tamsin
has reported a bug from manual testing
and it's up to us to fix it
Tamsin has helpfully documented the bug
as a failing scenario
Here it is
Hmm...
So let's try and figure out what
this is all about
Sean starts out with some credits
presumably that's what gives him premium status
As a result of that shout he's obviously
supposed to have some credits deducted
Tamsin's scenario says that the
correct behavior is to-for
5 credits to be deducted
leaving him with 25 credits
As we can see from running the test
the system is deducting 15 credits instead
Hmm I wonder why?
Let's read the whole feature
That should tell us some more about how
the system is supposed to behave
Oh my. This is very difficult to read
Apart from Tamsin's bug report scenario at the bottom
there's only one scenario and it's long!
I think I can count 12 steps altogether
excluding the background steps
The scenario has several When steps
which is often a sign that the scenario
is trying to test more than one
business rule at the time
We normally like to document the
business rules at the top of the feature
file
but that description section is left blank
so we haven't been left any clues there
Let's see if we can glean the rules
from the scenario
Sean starts out with 30 credits
and ends up with 11
But why?
There's so much detail here
I wonder which bits are important?
Could it be the number of words
Sean shouts that affect his credits
or the number of messages?
Based on Tamsin's test case
maybe the word buy is important
It's really hard to tell
It's interesting that Lucy hears
all Sean's messages
even these ones which look
to be over 180 characters
and would normally be blocked
Perhaps premium accounts get to
send messages over 180 characters
in exchange for credits?
Well...
the feature's pretty useless
as documentation of the behavior
It's no wonder there's a bug -
if this feature file reflects our team's
current understanding of
premium accounts behavior
I don't think we understand it very well
Let's try reading the code instead
OK
so we have a deduct_credits method here
that seems to encapsulate the rules
It looks like over long messages
messages that are not short enough
cost two credits
and each time the word buy is mentioned
we deduct five credits
It's a good job we know how to read code!
One of the promises of BDD
is that our feature files become the
single source of truth for the whole team
yet here the scenario does such a
poor job of documenting
what the system does we had to go
hunting for the truth in the code
That's fine for us because
we know how to read code
but it's excluded anyone on our team
who isn't technical
How would they be able to understand
the behavior of premium accounts at the moment?
We need to fix this feature file
It seems like a good time to ask
our domain experts for clarification
about this behavior
Ideally a three amigos meeting
would have done this already
but things don't always go
according to the script
Let's pay a visit to our product owner
Paula, the product owner, tells us
the rules are as follows:
Mention the word buy
and you lose 5 credits
Long messages cost 2 credits
OK, well that helps us a great deal but
this scenario is still doing a poor job
of illustrating those rules
Let's take a moment to understand why
It's all about the details when you're
first exploring a new domain problem
Details like the exact messages people
have shouted
are a great way to shine light
into the dark corners of your ignorance
They bring examples to life by
making them vivid and real
This encourages what creative people call
divergent thinking
which helps you discover
even more examples
as you explore the behavior
you need to provide
In BDD we call this
deliberate discovery
When we try to explore the
problem domain as thoroughly as we can
Details are good here
At some point however we need to
write a computer program
When that time comes we need to
switch to convergent thinking
and try to distill down all that detail
into something that clearly communicates
the essence of the behaviour
Now, too much detail can be distracting
or even misleading to our future readers
We call these incidental details
Let's try to distill the essence of this scenario
by removing the incidental details
We can start with this step
When Sean shouts "Come and buy a coffee"
What's important here is that
the shout contains the word buy
So let's write that
Better
We still have a little bit of detail -
the word buy -
but that's quite important
In fact, it helps to
illustrate our business rule
We'll need a new step def for this of course
We can just copy the code for
shouting a message from this step
down here for now
We will deal with this duplication, but later
Let's run Cucumber to check we haven't
made any mistakes
Good
Now we can use that same step
everywhere else in the scenario, too
We can apply the same pattern
to remove the noisy incidental details
from this next step too
What's the essence of this step?
In this case, it really doesn't matter
what Sean is shouting
A regular shout doesn't have any effect
on his premium account credits
So we could just re-word it like this
Again we'll need a new step definition,
and again, we'll just duplicate the code
for shouting a message for now
We'll run Cucumber again just in case...
And finally, let's use that new step
everywhere we can...
and run Cucumber once again
Now let's deal with this next step
What's the essence here?
Again, the exact words in the shout
don't have any significance
in this scenario
What matters, if anything
is that this is a long message
It's under 180 characters, but still longer
than a regular message
It's not clear how important this distinction is just yet
but let's give the authors of this scenario the benefit of the doubt for now
but push the details about the
message content
down into the step definition
following the same recipe
Again, we'll tolerate the duplication for now
and just generate a
180-character message here
Now what's interesting about this next step?
This shout is over out 180-character limit
After a quick chat with Paula,
we've confirmed that she wants to
call this an over long message
Let's update the rule we wrote up earlier
to document this evolution of our domain language
Then we can use that term in a new
more abstract step
Again, we'll make a step definition that
duplicates the shouting code
and this time make a
181-character message
just long enough to be over the
180-character limit
Right.
With the incidental details removed from these steps
it's starting to become easier
to see what's going on
It would be even easier if we
grouped them together
Let's do that
So now we can clearly see that Sean shouts three regular messages
a long message, two over long messages, and three messages containing the word buy
It's still a lot to digest but
a clearer picture is starting to emerge
Are there any other incidental details
remaining in this scenario?
Arguably
the steps that create
regular and long messages are incidental
since they have no bearing on the behavior
we're describing with this scenario
We can remove them altogether
and our behavior should be exactly the same
So let's do that
That's better
Now that we've removed all the incidental
detail it's much easier to see
how the figure of 11 credits has
been calculated:
two over long messages at
2 credits per message
and three messages containing
the word buy at 5 credits each
makes a total of 19 credits which
subtracted from the initial 30
makes 11
But we can make this even clearer.
These repetitive steps aren't necessary
They make the scenario look more like
a computer program than
a specification document
Instead of repeating the step
'When Sean shouts an over-long message'
over and over again...
let's just tell it like it is
We'll need a new step definition
for this one
The implementation of this step definition
is almost exactly the same as
the one below, we just need to
run a loop around it
based on the number specified
in the scenario
Again, we'll just suffer the duplication
for the time being
We have a nice trick up our sleeves
to get rid of all of it when the time comes
Let's do the exact same thing with these
other three steps
Again
we have the bulk of this code
that we can just copy and paste
adding a loop around the outside
Nice!
Now things are really getting
clearer
There is still a couple of problems
with this scenario
One is the name of this scenario
It really doesn't tell us anything at all
A great way to name your scenarios is to
think about how they named episodes of
the TV sitcom series Friends
Remember?
They were all called something like
'The one where Ross is fine' or
'The one where Phoebe gets married'
This is the one where...
well the one where
Sean shouts some over long messages
and some containing the word buy
Hmm... It's quite a complicated name
isn't it?
Maybe this scenario is doing too much!
...and that's the second problem
It's trying to test
both business rules at once
Normally, you'll want at least one scenario
for each business rule
that way each scenario clearly illustrates
the effect of that rule on the system
Sometimes it's interesting to also
document the effect that
multiple rules have when they play out
at the same time
But as you've already experienced
that can quickly get confusing
Sometimes you'll need several scenarios
to illustrate just one rule
In this case, one scenario for each rule
looks like it will be fine for the time being
Let's split this scenario in two
'The one where Shaun shouts
several over long messages'
...and
'The one where Sean shouts several
messages containing the word buy'
Great
Now the effect of each of these rules
is much more clearly documented
We run these new scenarios pass Paula
and she's delighted
She really likes how they read
She asks us - why do we still need
the original scenario?
Tamsin chimes in and says she has a
concern that the rules might conflict
with each other in the code somehow
As we talk about it we realize that while
we don't need this one anymore
there's a missing scenario where
both rules apply to the same message
'The one where there's a shout that's both overlong and with the word buy in it'
We'd better document that
as a question for now
While we have
Paula and Tamsin's attention
we ask a question we know often helps
to discover missing scenarios:
Is there another context that would result
in a different outcome here?
They both think about this
Tamsin suggests starting Sean out with
fewer credits
or shouting lots more messages
so that he runs out of credit
What would happen then?
Good question!
It looks like there's more to this feature
than we'd previously thought
We'll write that down as a question too
We still have a bug to fix!
Well that's been quite a session
We came in to fix one bug and ended up
having to fix our feature file first
We're still not done with that either
By pushing the incidental details down
out of the scenario into the step definitions
we've made a mess of duplication
in the step definitions
There's a neat fix for that
but we'll have to save that for next time
Let's reflect on what we've learned
When scenarios are very heavy in detail they can be confusing to read
We call these incidental details
when they are just noise
that detracts from communicating
the essence of the scenario
Scenarios that are heavy in detail
are sometimes said to be written in an
imperative style
They contain lots of how
and not much what
We often use this style when we're
working on a brand new domain problem
and are still grasping for an understanding
We just want to write something down
As your confidence in your
domain knowledge improves
you'd expect to feel comfortable
removing some of these details
Scenarios with more abstract steps
like this are said to be written in a
declarative style
Using a more declarative style
might mean
you'll need to find names for things like
the way we had to name
an over long message
This discovery of your
ubiquitous domain language
is a great side effect of
distilling the essence of your scenarios
Now you have a bigger vocabulary
that you can use all the way
down through your code
and in your future conversations too
One downside, as you've seen,
of pushing the how down
from your scenarios into
the step definitions
is that the step definition code
becomes more complex
Some teams reject this
and prefer to use a simple vocabulary
of step definitions leaving more detail
in their scenarios
There are no right and wrong answers here
but if you have sufficient competence with code
you'll easily be able to handle that
extra bit of complexity and keep
readability top of your priority list
That's what we'll work on next time
Bye for now!
Captions created by Jayson Smith for Cucumber Ltd.