Hello, and welcome to the second lesson
here at Cucumber School!
Last time we learned how to use
conversations about concrete examples
to explore your problem domain
and decide what to build
In this episode, you'll learn how to
describe those examples using the
Gherkin specification language
so that Cucumber can run them
Then, we'll drive out a solution using
a failing Cucumber scenario to guide us
There's going to be a fair amount
of programming in this episode
and some object-oriented design as well
We want this to feel real,
so we'll work on something fun
A social networking application!
Shouty is a social network that allows
people who are physically close to communicate
just like people have always communicated
with their voices
In the real world you can talk to someone
in the same room or across the street
or even a hundred metres
away from you in a park
if you shout
That's Shouty!
What you say in this social network
can only be heard by people who are nearby
Let's start with a very basic example
of Shouty's behaviour
Something we might have discussed
in a Three Amigos meeting
Sean the shouter shouts,
"Free bagels at Sean's!"
And Lucy the listener
who happens to be stood across the street
from his store 15 metres away, hears him
She walks into Sean's coffee shop
and takes advantage of the offer
We can translate this into a Gherkin scenario
so that Cucumber can run it
Here's how that would look
You can see that there are four
special keywords being used here
Scenario just tells Cucumber we're about
to describe an example that it can execute
Then you see the lines beginning with
Given, When, and Then
Given is the context for the scenario
We're putting the system into a specific state
ready for the scenario to unfold
When is the action
Something that happens to the system that will
cause something else to happen: an outcome
Then is the outcome
It's the behaviour we expect from the system
when this action happens in this context
You'll notice we've omitted from our outcome
anything about Lucy walking into Sean's
store and making a purchase
Remember, Gherkin is supposed to
describe the behaviour of the system
so it would be distracting to have
that detail in our scenario
Each scenario has these three ingredients:
a context, an action, and one or more outcomes
Together, they describe one single aspect
of the behaviour of the system
Now that we've translated our
example into Gherkin
we can automate it
Before we get started
make sure you have a modern version
of Ruby installed and the Bundler gem
Open a command prompt and type
If you see an error message
when you run these commands
you'll need to fix your Ruby installation
Go back to the command prompt
and create a new directory for our project
Use 'cd' to go into that directory
and open it up in your editor
First, we'll create a gemfile that describes
the Ruby gems we need for our project
We'll add Cucumber and RSpec expectations
Now go back to the command line
and run 'bundle install'
to install these gems
Now we're ready!
If we run Cucumber at this point
you'll see it's telling us
to create a features directory
That's the conventional place to
store your Gherkin specifications
Let's create one
Now we're ready to create our
first feature file
Call the file shouty.feature
All feature files start with the keyword
feature followed by a name
It's a good convention to give it
a name that matches the file name
Now let's write out our first scenario
Switch back to the command prompt
and run 'cucumber'
You'll see Cucumber has found
a feature file and read it back to us
We can see a summary of
the results at the bottom:
three steps, one scenario, all undefined
Undefined means Cucumber
doesn't know what to do
for any of the three steps
we wrote in our Gherkin scenario
It needs us to provide it with
some step definitions
Step definitions translate
from the plain language
you use in Gherkin, into code
When Cucumber runs a step
it looks for a step definition
that matches the text in the step
If it finds one, then it
executes the code in the step definition
If it doesn't find one
well you've just seen what happens
Cucumber helpfully prints out
some code snippets that we can use
as a basis for new step definitions
Let's copy these
We'll paste them into a Ruby file
under a new directory called
step_definitions
underneath the features directory
I'll just call it 'steps.rb'
Now run Cucumber again
This time the output is a little different
We now have a pending step
and two skipped ones
This means Cucumber found all our
step definitions and executed the first one
But that first step definition
throws a Pending exception
which causes Cucumber to stop,
skip the rest of the steps
and mark the scenario as pending
It's time to work on our solution
At this point we need to do
a little domain modeling
The words in the step
provide us some good hints
about some names that
will appear in our domain model
Our scenario mentions
two people Lucy and Sean
so it looks like we'll need
a couple of person objects at least
Each person will also need to
know their own location
Cucumber is telling us to
write the code we wish we had
Let's do it!
Start by renaming the 'arg1' parameter
to something that better reflects its meaning
We'll call it distance
To keep things simple
we're going to assume
all people are situated on a line
A one-dimensional coordinate system
We can always introduce proper geo locations later
We'll place Sean in the center
and Lucy 15 metres away from Sean
Notice that the number 15
does not appear anywhere in our code
The value 15 is automatically passed
from the Gherkin step into the step definition
If you're curious
that's the '\d' in the
pattern of the step definition
We'll explain regular expressions
in detail in a future lesson
To implement this step
we need to create a couple of
person objects with
the specified distance between them
We could write it like this
Now we have two instances
of person one representing Lucy
and one representing Sean
If you run Cucumber we'll see
a compilation error from Ruby
We need to define our person class
Let's give our solution a home
by creating a 'lib' directory
We'll put our Shouty application
in a Ruby file called 'shouty.rb' in that directory
Create the bare bones of our person
just enough to satisfy the API
that we know we need
from the code we've written
in our step definitions
For now, we'll just require the
Shouty application from our 'steps.rb' file
In a later lesson, we'll talk more
about how to organize this code a bit better
When we run the scenario again
the first step is green!
We'll follow the same flow
to make the remaining two steps pass
do a little bit of domain modeling,
write the code we wish we had,
make it compile, and run the scenario
In the second step definition,
we want to tell Sean to shout something
In order to send instructions to Sean,
we need to store him in an instance variable
so that he'll be accessible
from all of our definitions, like this
Our Person class needs a 'shout' method
Let's add it!
Don't worry about the implementation yet
The important thing right now is to
discover the shape of our domain model
The last step definition is where
we implement the check or assertion
We'll verify that what Lucy has heard
is exactly the same as what Sean shouted
Once again we're going to
write the code we wish we had
So we need a way to ask Lucy
what messages she's heard
and we also need to know
what it was that Sean shouted
We can record what Sean shouts
by storing it an instance variable
as the When step runs
This is a common pattern to use
in Cucumber step definitions
when you don't want to repeat
the same test data in different
parts of a scenario
Now we can use that value in the assertion check
We also need to add a 'messages_heard'
method to our Person class
Let's do that now
We run Cucumber again and
and whoops!
Undefined method 'messages_heard'
for nil class steps line 15
It looks like we forgot to set Lucy as an
instance variable
Let's fix that and run the test again
This is great!
Whenever we do BDD, getting to our
first failing test is a milestone
Seeing the test fail, proves that it is
capable of detecting errors in our code
Never trust an automated test that
you haven't seen fail!
Now all we have to do is write
the code to make it pass
That's the easy bit!
In this case we're going to cheat
We have a one line fix that will
make the scenario pass
It's not a particularly
future-proof implementation
Can you guess what it is?
I'll show you
Hmm, there. I told you it
wasn't very future-proof!
Still, the fact that such a poor
implementation can pass our tests
shows us that we need to work on our tests
A more comprehensive set of scenarios would
force us to write a better implementation
This is the essence of
behaviour-driven development
Examples of behaviour drive the development
So we know we need more scenarios
and a better solution
Instead of writing a note on our to-do list
let's write another failing scenario
Now when we come back to this code
we can just run the tests
and Cucumber will remind us
what we need to do next
We're done for the day!
Go make yourself a cup of tea
Captions created by Jayson Smith for Cucumber Ltd.