Welcome to the final lesson in
this series of Cucumber School
Over the series we've tried to cover
all the important techniques
and concepts we think you need to become a
successful behaviour-driven developer
We've taught you how to break down
requirements with example mapping
and how to express those examples
as Gherkin scenarios
We've explained the importance of
keeping your features readable
and shown you how to write great, flexible
step definitions to help you achieve that goal
We've also explored the difference between
acceptance tests and unit tests
and demonstrated how the outside in
approach to software development works
using both types of tests
to drive out the solution to your
stakeholders' problems
One glaring omission from
the story so far however
is that our Shouty solution is
nothing more than a domain model
It doesn't have any way for
a user to interact with it
Well, that's all about to change
In this episode, we'll review the code
that's just been written
for the first iteration of
Shouty's web user interface
and show you how to use Selenium WebDriver
a browser automation library to run our
Cucumber scenarios through that user interface
We think it would be irresponsible
to teach you how to use Selenium
without also teaching you about the Agile
testing pyramid and its nemesis
the testing ice cream cone
We've come across too many teams
who have ended up with
miserably slow, unreliable test suites
that cost too much to maintain
because all their Cucumber scenarios
go through the UI
It doesn't have to be this way
and in this episode
we'll show you how to avoid this trap
Let's start by walking you through
the changes that have been happening
in the code base while we've been away
Shouty now has a simple web UI
which displays a form
where a user can shout a message
It won't win any awards for style just yet
but it should be functional at least
We can let Cucumber put the new web app
through its paces
by setting the shouty.testDepth
system property to web
when we run Cucumber
This setting causes the scenarios
to be run through the browser via Selenium
and if you watch closely
you can see the message being typed
into the form as it runs
You can see it's way slower
to run the scenarios via browser
Luckily, we still have our original
much faster version of the acceptance tests
that go directly to the domain model
These run in less than a second
We can run this version by setting
shouty.testDepth to something else
or just leaving it out altogether
Nice!
So we have the best of both worlds it seems
Let's have a look at how this
has been implemented in the features
In the constructor of the Stepdefs class, here
we’re declaring a parameter of type ShoutSupport
This is an abstract class, and we have two
concrete implementations of that class -
DomainShoutSupport and WebShoutSupport
Over here, in CustomPicoFactory
we decide which one to use
based on the shouty.testDepth
system property
We’re telling Cucumber to use this custom
implementation of ObjectFactory
here in cucumber.properties
Both DomainShoutSupport
and WebShoutSupport are polymorphic -
meaning they implement the exact same set of
methods defined in ShoutSupport
As far as the step definitions are concerned
they’re interchangeable
This allows us to use different strategies
for automating the application
DomainShoutSupport contains the familiar
automation code that calls
the domain model directly
WebShoutSupport, on the other hand, is where we
automate Shouty through its new web UI
As you can see, there’s quite a bit
more work being done here
These hooks, startServer and stopServer
start and stop the web server
so that we can be confident there will be no
state leaking from one scenario to the next
This hook, closeAllBrowsers makes sure to close
any open browsers at the end of each scenario
The implementation of seanShout is very different
to the one that hits the domain model directly
First, we 'log in' as Sean -
in fact this just opens the homepage for the app
putting the user’s name in the query string
The browser here is an instance of Selenium’s
FirefoxDriver class
We keep all the browsers used in the scenario
in a Map, with one browser per person
We use the getBrowserFor method to fetch
a browser for Sean
then assign that as the current browser
Next, the shout method asks WebDriver to
find the message box on the form
then types out the contents of the message
into the box
Next, it finds the form’s submit button
and clicks it
Let’s walk through what happens when
a scenario runs using webShoutSupport
When Cucumber runs the
'Sean shouts Free Bagels' step
it searches for the corresponding step definition
and executes the method in the StepDefs class
Now, the code in that step definition calls
the seanShout method on shoutSupport
which is an instance of WebShoutSupport
which in turn creates a WebDriver
and calls the get method on it to
open the homepage as Sean
Selenium WebDriver now tells Firefox to
open a browser at that URL
and when the browser opens that URL
our web server will get a request for the page
We render the page on the server
and the browser displays it
Next, WebShoutSupport asks Selenium to fill out
and submit the shout form
which causes button clicks in the browser
The form is submitted to the server
and the server calls the core domain
to broadcast the shout
In contrast, domainShoutSupport’s implementation
of seanShout calls the domain model directly
Notice this is exactly the same code
as the web server uses
The strategy that talks directly
to the core domain model
gives us fast feedback
and lets us test where the
heart of the application's behaviour
is implemented
We've now added a second strategy
that allows us to prove this behaviour
still works when presented via the web UI
You might be wondering why we need both?
Why didn't we just start driving our way in
from the web UI in the beginning?
We've found that focusing on driving out
a domain model from our scenarios first
modelling by example
gives us fast feedback about
our understanding of new problem domains
We don't get distracted by
solution domain complexities like
web servers, HTML, and so on
while we're still just trying to understand
the core of the problem
In the long run, we also find that
staying focussed on the core domain
helps us build scenarios that are
more stable over time
User interfaces tend to change
a lot more often
than the core business rules of the domain
Building scenarios that make sense
even without a user interface
also helps us to avoid
our tests from becoming too
Imperative
Most teams who write and run their cukes
against the user interface
end it with a lot of incidental detail
in their scenarios about the UI interaction
Solution domain stuff
These scenarios are poor documentation
They're too busy talking about
how the user performs a task
rather than what the user is trying to achieve
For example we might have written
the scenario like this instead
This scenario doesn't illustrate
the behaviour very well
If you didn't know anything about Shouty
and were trying to understand it
through the examples written like this
you'd have a tough time
It makes for lousy documentation
Notice how the language used in this scenario
the URLs, the CSS selectors
even the filling in fields
and clicking of buttons
is from the solution domain
not the problem domain
It tells you nothing about
your team's ubiquitous language
Finally, this scenario is brittle
If you need to change the details
of the interaction for sending a shout
such as the way you authenticate
you'd need to come back
and change every scenario that involves shouting
By pushing the how down
your scenarios will remain truer for longer
The opposite of the imperative style
where we express the scenarios
using problem domain language is known as a
Declarative Style
In this style, we try to describe
what the user is trying to achieve
rather than how they do it
Thanks to the declarative style
we've been using through the rest of the series
we were able to easily swap in a
different strategy for automating
our application through the web
without changing our specifications
If there are other interfaces to our application
like a rest API or a mobile app
we can continue to use this pattern
adding new strategies
that run our scenarios through
these new layers of the stack
Remember, each of these strategies uses
exactly the same scenarios and step definitions
This means the investment you put into
writing your scenarios pays back over and over
as you reuse them to validate
the behaviour of the application
from these different perspectives
This is a major advantage of having
pushed the details of how Sean shouts
down into a helper method
If this detail was still up
in the step definition
or worse, in the scenario itself
we wouldn't have this flexibility
In general, the structure emerging
in our application and test code
is called a ports and adapters architecture, or
Hexagonal Architecture
You can think of ports and adapters
as a direct analogy
to physical devices with plugs and sockets
For example, the HDMI port on this laptop
lets me plug in any kind of display
that also has a HDMI port
If I need to use a VGA display
I can use an adapter between the two
In a hexagonal architecture
the inner hexagon contains
your core business logic
This is where the if statements that
deliver the most value to your stakeholders
should live
The inner hexagon knows nothing about
the outside world:
your web servers, your databases, your email
sending service, or your enterprise message bus
It's pure business logic
We expose this core behaviour via
one or more ports
A port is really just a protocol
an API if you like
Any component who understands that protocol
can then plug in and interact
with the core through the port
We call that component an adapter
It's the adapter's job to expose
the core domain logic to the outside world
In Shouty, there's just one port
the API to our domain model
made up of the Person and Network classes
We've plugged in two different adapters
to this little port:
the WebApp, which exposes
Shouty's core domain over the web
for users (or Selenium WebDriver)
to interact with
And DomainShoutSupport
which lets Cucumber
drive the application directly
Both are clients of the same API
The hexagonal architecture is a terrific fit
for teams who care about testability
In fact, it was invented precisely
to allow for testability
back in the days when thick client GUIs
were impossible to automate
By separating the core domain logic from the GUI
these TDD pioneers were able to plug
their tests into the same port as the GUI
and still test most of
the application's behaviour
If you have the discipline
to keep your code separated like this
you benefit from being able to
run the tests
against the most business-valuable
lines of code in your codebase
the core domain
in the shortest amount of time
Tests that hit pure business logic
can run lightning fast
meaning it's cheap to get
really thorough feedback
about whether that logic is behaving correctly
Let's get back to the code
To give us a way to test the app manually
the Shouty developers have kindly added this
ManualTestServer class
which starts the web server pre-configured
with some familiar test data
This means we're able to
test the web app
without having to create accounts for people -
a feature we don't have yet!
So we should be able to
open our browser tab as Sean
then another tab as Lucy
send a shout from Sean
refresh Lucy's page and see-
wait a minute! Where's Sean Shout?
This is odd -
The scenario is passing
but there's nothing appearing on Lucy's page
What's going on?
The answer lies in the implementation
of our Then step
Reading it, we can see that
the step definition
is going directly to the domain model
to discover the messages
that Lucy has heard
This shouldn't have been a surprise to us -
it's always been that way -
but since our When step now hits the UI
we would expect this Then step
to also adopt the same strategy
When you start to mix different
depths of testing as we’re doing here
a good rule of thumb is to keep the depth of your
When and Then steps consistent
It’s often advisable to bypass layers
and reach down deeper into the stack
to set up state in the Given steps
But if we carry out an action via the UI
the outcome check in the Then step
should also be done through the UI
Let’s remedy this situation by
pushing the code in this step definition
into a helper method
Then we’ll be able to have
two different strategies
for checking the messages
that a user has heard
Once we have a failing test for
the web strategy
we can drive out the behaviour in the UI
to display the user’s messages
We’ll focus on a single scenario
while we do this work
Once we’ve got that one passing
to our satisfaction
we can apply the same change across
the rest of the scenarios
This very basic scenario, where Lucy hears Sean
is a good place to start
Let's extract a method, getMessagesHeardBy
from the body of the step definition
and put it in our DomainShoutSupport
That scenario is still passing
Good
Now, when we run it through the web
we’re shown we need to add
that method to WebShoutSupport
How will we fetch the messages heard?
The first thing we’ll need to do is log in
to make sure we’re reading the messages
for the correct user
So we can reuse this
helper method we’ve already built
Now, we’ll need to
scrape the messages off the HTML page
Remember we’re going test-first here
so we don’t have this markup yet
That's not a problem
We can use the test to help us design
what the markup should look like
Let’s assume that each message will be
an element with a message class on it
We can ask Selenium to give us all
the elements with that class
That gives us a list of
Selenium WebDriver Elements
which we can then transform into
a list of their text content
Let's watch this test fail
That looks OK.
Let's play fake it till you make it
just to check this assertion
is doing the right thing
We’ll hard-code the HTML we want
into the template, here
This gives us a chance to
talk with our designer about the markup
We go over for a chat and he loves it
so we can press on!
The next step is to
make the HTML template dynamic
and have it display the actual list of
messages heard by the user
We could continue using the
Cucumber scenario to drive this out
but it would be better to zoom in and focus
on some unit tests for the web app now
That way, if this behaviour ever
slips loose in the future
there will be a unit test pointing us
to exactly where we need to go to fix it
Luckily, the web app has already been built
with some unit tests around it
These tests load the HttpServlet in isolation
passing in a map of people
that just contains test doubles
We could have used real instances
from our core domain model
but as we explained in the last episode
using test doubles helps us to see
the protocol on the port between the web app
adapter and our core domain
We’ve abstracted some of the nitty-gritty
of calling the Servlet into a base class
which you can examine for yourself
We need a new test for the GET request
which simulates the situation where
Lucy has heard a couple of messages
and views her homepage
We’d expect to be able to find the message text
in each of the message elements
When we run this, it fails because
we’re just hard-coding the message at the moment
Let’s TDD our solution
If you’d like to try this yourself
just pause the video here and
see if you can figure out what to do next
before we show you
Starting in the template, we can look for
a local variable, let’s call it messagesHeard
and iterate over it
For each message, we’ll write a message element
There
Now we need to set that messagesHeard
variable for the template
We do that from within the doGet request handler
method in the web servlet
We need to put the messagesHeard into this context map
Helpfully we have this getUser method that
fetches the right user from the people map
based on the query string parameter used in the request
Let’s give that a try
Great! Suddenly everything is green
Try a quick manual test for yourself
creating a couple of tabs as Sean and Lucy
and satisfy yourself that it’s working now
Now that we’ve proved our
getMessagesHeardBy method
works for both domain and web strategies
let’s use that method in
all the step definitions
so that every scenario
that checks for messagesHeard
will do that check in a consistent way
This is just a matter of finding each call
to ask a Person domain object for messagesHeard
and converting it to use
our new helper method instead
Let's run all the scenarios in the shout feature
Great. It looks like we're done
If we look at the other feature
Premium accounts
we can see that there’s
a similar problem to the one we’ve just resolved
This last step
'Then Sean should have n credits'
goes direct to the domain model
to check Sean’s credits
rather than having that
extra layer of indirection
that would allow us to use a domain
or a web strategy for the check
It will be useful practice for you
to go through and apply
exactly what we just did to this step definition
We'll leave that as an exercise for you
Let's fast-forward to the point
where this is done
Now, we can run all of our scenarios
at both levels
against the domain, and against the web UI
This is awesome!
Isn't it?
We've talked a lot about the benefits of
automated tests in this series
but let’s consider the flip side for a moment
and look at the costs
Every automated test in your system
comes at a cost
You have the cost of
writing it in the first place
the cost of waiting for it to run each time
the cost of changing it when the
desired behaviour of the application changes
and the cost of debugging it
when it fails for no good reason
When the majority of your tests hit
the application through the user interface
you get a great benefit
from knowing that each scenario
is using the system exactly as a user would
Yet the downside is that
these tests are much slower to run
and are often also much less reliable
A well-known metaphor to help you
think about this problem is the
Agile Testing Pyramid
At the base of the pyramid
you have a large number of unit tests
shallow tests that directly hit isolated
individual classes and modules in your solution
The pyramid gets narrower as you go up
indicating that as the depth of tests increases
the less of them you should have
At the very top of the pyramid
where the tests go right through
the whole application stack
you want as few as possible
Just enough to give you confidence
the thing is working
When you drive most of
your behaviour through the GUI
you end up with the opposite -
more of a testing ice cream cone
Now I love an ice cream on a hot summer’s day
but when your test suite looks like this
you’re waiting hours for test results
and there are generally at least
one or two random failures in every build
Although we have the choice to
run every Shouty scenario through the GUI
the Agile Testing Pyramid tells us
that would be a bad idea
We need to select a few representative or
key examples to run through the web UI
and run the rest through the domain
How do we choose those key examples?
Let’s try and think about
what could possibly go wrong
We want to identify the minimum number of
scenarios that would give us confidence
the system is working
Remember: both our core domain
and our web server
are protected by their own unit tests
so we just need a few checks
for basic correctness
Would it be enough to just test this scenario
the one where the listener is within range?
If we did that, what could possibly go wrong?
With our tester’s hat on
we can imagine a bug
where the web server’s template
didn’t render multiple messages
This scenario only works for one
So we could add this scenario
the one where there are two shouts
Yet we’d easily catch that bug in manual testing
and could then pin it down with
a unit test on the web server
So we don’t need to run this as a
full-stack test every time
In fact
to do so would be wasteful
How about the scenario about
the listener being out of range?
If we skip that in our web-depth Cucumber run
would we leave ourselves vulnerable
to a dangerous bug?
Well, it’s true that if people heard messages
that were not meant for them
it could make us look pretty bad
But how likely is this to happen?
That logic is all in the core domain
the web server just renders
the messages returned by the core
So there’s almost a zero risk of
this bug ever leaking out
Again, a full-stack test for this
behaviour would be wasteful
Although the same goes for
the logic about a long message
we know that there’s potential for
there to be bugs in the interaction
of the UI for longer messages
so it makes sense for us to run this one
Let’s mark it up as @high-risk
and mark the one where the listener is
within range as @high-impact
We’ll explain these terms in a moment
Now, we can run the tests at the top of our pyramid
using those tags and the web testDepth setting
Now we have three different levels of tests in
our pyramid that we want to run to check our code
The unit tests
the core domain acceptance tests
and the key examples running as full-stack tests
Let's set up our maven configuration to run
all of these tests first with a single command
Maven already runs our unit and domain-level
acceptance tests automatically
using the surefire plugin
We can add extra configuration to our pom.xml
to tell surefire to run a second execution
of the tests with different configuration
Just add a surefire plugin node like this
then an execution node with an id of
web-acceptance-tests
Now we attach it to the test goal -
the one maven runs by default
We configure the execution by excluding
all the unit tests -
no need to run those again
and setting the argline to use
the testDepth of web
with the Cucumber options set to run
only those scenarios tagged
as either high impact or high risk
There
Now when we run `mvn test`
from the command-line
it runs all three layers of our testing pyramid
starting from the bottom up
One last thing:
When we automate web pages, we need to
refer to user interface elements and actions
buttons, links, text, clicks, etc
This is solution domain jargon
we’ve managed to keep out of our scenarios
and that’s good!
But it has to go somewhere
On larger projects, it becomes useful
to create abstractions called
page objects to represent
the things being filled in
clicked, and examined for content
For example, we might have a homepage object
with a method called shout
that encapsulated the calls to interact
with the elements on the web page
This allows you to easily reuse code
and keep it easy to read
You can easily build page objects on your own
but if you’re feeling lazy
Selenium ships with a PageFactory class
that reduces the amount of boilerplate code
you need to write
The page objects pattern is a great fit
for keeping your web automation code tidy
but we strongly recommend that you try to
push as many of your tests
down the pyramid first
You can use page objects together with
a hexagonal architecture pattern
we’ve shown you in this episode
so that when you do need to hit the web UI
you can do that through neat and tidy code
That's it kids, school's out!
Time to step out into the real world
This has been an intense episode
and we’ve thrown a lot of new concepts at you -
the hexagonal architecture, the strategy
pattern and the agile testing pyramid
Please take time to watch this video over
a few times until you understand these concepts
and study the exercises and reflection questions
We want you to remember that acceptance tests
don’t have to be full-stack tests
In fact, it’s often a mistake if they are
Don’t fall into the trap of building yet another
testing ice cream cone for your project
Have developers and testers work side-by-side
to maximise the value you get
from your testing investment
by pushing as many tests
as you can down to the lowest level
The responsibility for the health and wellbeing
of the world’s Cucumber suites rests with you now
Use your knowledge wisely!
If you remember one thing from
the video series, remember this:
The software you write is just a model -
a model of your team's understanding
of the problem domain
The better that understanding is
the better the software will be
Put your effort into understanding
the problem together
and the software will take care of itself
Goodbye from all of us on Cucumber School
and have fun out there!
Captions created by Jayson Smith for Cucumber Ltd.