Welcome back to the 3rd lesson of Cucumber School
I hope you're having fun!
Last time we showed you the
fundamental components
of a Cucumber test suite
and how we use them to drive out a solution
test first
First, we specified the behaviour we wanted
using a Gherkin scenario in a feature file
Then we wrote step definitions to translate
the plain English from our scenario
into concrete actions in code
The step definitions then exercised our
very basic domain model
for the Shouty application
We tend to think of the code that
actually pokes around with the system
as distinct from the step definitions
so we’ve drawn an extra box labelled
'automation code'
Automation code can do
almost anything to your application:
it can drive a web browser around your site
make HTTP requests to a REST API
or -- as you’ve already seen --
drive a domain model directly
Automation code is a big topic
that we’ll come back to
First we want to concentrate on step definitions
Good step definitions are important because
they enable the readability of your scenarios
The better you are at matching
plain language phrases from Gherkin
the more expressive you can be
when writing scenarios
Teams who do this well refer to their
features as living documentation -
a specification document that
never goes out of date
In Cucumbe,r we use regular expressions to match
plain language phrases from Gherkin steps
Regular expressions have quite an
intimidating reputation
In fact, there are only
a handful of patterns you need
to be able to do almost anything
with regular expressions
No need to be scared
We’ll cover all of those patterns
in this lesson
Let’s look at the Shouty scenario
from the last lesson
As Cucumber starts to execute this feature,
it will come to the first step of the scenario
'Given Lucy is 15 metres from Sean'
and say to itself 'now - do I have any
step definitions that match the phrase:
Lucy is 15 metres from Sean?'
The most simple regular expression that
would match that step is this one
That’s pretty simple isn’t it?
Regular expressions are just patterns
and the most simple pattern
you can use is a perfect match
In Java, we can use this pattern
to make a step definition like this
We use an annotation to link
the regular expression to the Java method
We can call the method whatever we like
but it make sense to
have it be something meaningful
We use underscores rather than
the standard camel case naming
so that the method reads
just like a sentence
Notice that
unlike the snippet generated by Cucumber
that we used in the previous lesson
this step definition doesn’t take an argument
To capture interesting values
from our step definitions
we can use what’s called a capture group
You just surround the interesting part
of the pattern with parentheses, like this
Now we’re capturing that value as an argument
The value 15 will be passed
to our code automatically by Cucumber
That’s not much better yet though -
this step definition will only match
if the step specifies a distance of 15 metres
If we want to set Lucy and Sean
a different distance apart
this pattern won’t match
Let's try it and see
Yep, it’s showing this step as undefined.
Hmm... So that’s not much use
We need to make our regular expression
a little bit more flexible
We can do this using a wildcard
There are a few different ways to specify
a wildcard in a regular expression
One of the simplest is alternation
where we express different options
separated by a pipe character (|), like this
Now we could use either of those
values in the step
and this definition will still match
and pass the value into our code
Alternation is useful when
you have a fixed set of values
but normally you’ll want something a bit looser
The dot (.) is a metacharacter
which means it has magical powers
in a regular expression
It means match any single character
so we could change our step definition
to this instead
Now we’ll match a step with
any two-digit distance
That’s an improvement
but we can still do better
Remember, the dot will match
any character at all
so it would also match letters
as well as numbers
We’ll come back to this problem in a minute
More pressing is that we are limited
to using two-digit distances
What if we wanted to place them
2 metres apart, or 100?
To fix that, we need to use a modifier
In regular expressions, a repetition modifier
comes after a character
and tells us how many times
that character can appear
The most flexible modifier is the star (*)
We could use it like this
The star means any number of times
so dot-star (.*) means any character
any number of times
That’s pretty flexible!
Actually, maybe a bit too flexible
Remember the dot will match any character
including letters
Combined with the star
we could end up matching a step like this:
Hmm... Our capture would gobble up everything
up until the words metres from Sean
Look what our distance argument ends up as!
We need to be more specific
Luckily, the dot isn’t the only
special character we can use
Regular expressions allow you
to define character classes
A character class is
a range of characters
one of which must match at
that point in the pattern
You just place all of the acceptable characters
together inside square brackets
So we can replace our dot with
a character class that accepts
any single digit from 0 to 9, like this
Now we’re accepting any digit from 0-9
any number of times
But we can do better than that
With a continuous range of characters
we don’t need to specify each one
That works just the same, and reads a bit better
For common character classes like digits
there are a few shorthand character classes
that you can use
For digits, you can use a backslash-d (\d)
When we write a regular expression in Java
we have to escape backslashes and double quotes
with an additional backslash
So when you see two backslashes,
think of them as a single one
Maybe you find that’s just made your
regular expression more cryptic
It’s something of a matter of taste
but there are only a few of these
to learn if you’re interested
Here are the most useful ones:
\d is for digit
\w is for word character
\s is for whitespace:
a space, a tab, or a line break
The star modifier has a subtle flaw:
any number of times includes zero times
We don’t want to match distances with
zero digits in them
This time Cucumber throws an error
and fails our step!
It doesn’t know how to convert
an empty string into an integer!
To fix this, we can use the plus (+) modifier
That means at least once
which is more suitable in this situation
Now that is pretty watertight
We took quite a long time to get here
but on the journey we passed through almost
every feature of regular expressions
you’ll ever need to work with Cucumber
There are just a couple more
we want to tell you about
Don’t go thinking you’re limited to
capturing just one argument from a step
You can use the parentheses as many times
as you like in your pattern
For example, we could make the names of the people
in our step into arguments, like this
Notice that we haven’t used quotation marks ("")
to surround our captures
anywhere in this lesson
There’s nothing mandatory about doing that -
it's just a convention that
many people like to use
but as long as you use a capture group
in your regular expression
Cucumber will pass you the captured value
as an argument
Although it’s important to try to use
consistent terminology in your Gherkin scenarios
to help develop the
ubiquitous language of your domain
you also want scenarios to read naturally
which means allowing a bit of flexibility
Ideally, the language used in scenarios should
never be constrained by your step definitions
Otherwise, they’ll end up sounding
like they were written by robots
One common example is the problem of plurals
Suppose we want to place Lucy and Sean
just 1 metre apart
This step would not match
Because we’ve used the singular 'metre'
instead of the plural 'metres'
we don’t have a match
What a pain!
Fear not!
We can use another modifier
the question mark (?)
to mark the “s” as optional
Here's how that looks
The question mark is one way to
smooth off some of the rough edges
in your regular expressions
Another trick is to use a non-capturing group
Suppose someone wanted to write this step
The fact that Lucy is standing
doesn't particularly matter
but the people writing this step
like the way it reads, and want to keep it
We can change our regular expression
to allow for both, like this
This is the same as the
alternates we used earlier
We use a list of alternate phrases
separated by a pipe
This time we start with
the question-mark-colon (?:)
to indicate that the group is non-capturing
Otherwise we’d be passed the value
of whichever alternate matched
which isn’t really interesting to us
One final thing
You might have noticed that the snippets
Cucumber prints out for undefined steps
start with a caret (^) and end with a dollar ($)
Those two metacharacters are called anchors
because they’re used to tie down
the regular expression
to the beginning and end
of the string they're being matched on
You don’t have to use them, and we’ve got on fine
leaving them out of this example so far
To illustrate why we need them
consider this step
Because we haven’t anchored down the
end of our pattern with a dollar
it will happily match this step
including that bit about Dave at the end
Adding anchors to the beginning and end
of your pattern
prevents this kind of nasty little accident
When Cucumber captures an argument from your step
it’s always a string by default
even if you’ve used a digit character class
in the regular expression
Cucumber is smart enough to convert that string
into the declared type of the method parameter
Cucumber can convert strings into
any of Java’s number types
It can even convert into enum values and dates!
Well, that was a pretty deep dive
into regular expressions!
With what you’ve learned in this lesson
you’ll be able to match any phrase
you see in a Gherkin step without fear
This will help you keep your scenarios readable
and keep your business stakeholders
engaged in the BDD process
We’d love to hear your feedback
about Cucumber School
If you love it, feel free to tweet about us
and mention @cucumberbdd
in your tweet if you like
If there’s anything you’d like us to improve on
or any specific things you want to tell us
please email hello@cucumber.pro
to start the conversation
Captions created by Jayson Smith for Cucumber Ltd.