Welcome back to Cucumber School
Last time we worked on cleaning up the
Shouty features to keep them in sync
with the current status of the project
We stripped the scenarios back
to only specify the behaviour
of passing messages between people
We made it clear that the proximity rule
had not yet been implemented
You’ll remember from the
regular expressions lesson
how important it is to be
expressive in your scenarios
and keep them readable
In this episode we’re going to learn some
new tricks with Gherkin that will give you
even more flexibility about
how you write scenarios
Once again, the Shouty pixies --
Umm... -- I mean the Shouty developers --
have been hard at work
implementing that proximity rule
Let's have a look at how they got on
Right, so those two scenarios
we just left as just placeholders:
the one where the listener is within range
and the one where the listener is out of range
have been fleshed out, and are passing
Fantastic!
Let’s review the changes to
the feature file in more detail
We now have four scenarios:
our original two from the last time we
looked at the code, and the two new ones
With the two new ones fleshed out
we can see that the first scenario we wrote -
the one where the listener hears a message -
is identical to the third one -
the one where the listener is within range
Keeping excess scenarios is wasteful:
they clutter up your feature files
distracting your readers
When you run your features as tests
excess scenarios make them
take longer to run than necessary
The one where the listener is within range
is a perfectly good way of checking that
the message has been sent correctly
Let's remove the other one
Similarly, we no longer really need
to be testing multiple messages
We used this test to triangulate
and force us to replace
the hard-coded message output
with a proper implementation
Now we have a domain model that uses
a variable for the message
there's an insignificant chance
of this behaviour regressing
so we can safely remove the test
So now we’re down to two scenarios
that illustrate this rule about proximity:
the one where the listener is within range
and the one where the listener is out of range
We’re using two different listeners, Lucy,
who’s always within range, and Larry, who’s not
It’s always Sean who’s doing the shouting
We create all three people here, in the background
Notice that we also specify the range here
We could have just hard-coded it within the system
but having it documented here in the scenario
helps to make the behaviour we’ve specified
much easier to understand
A happy side-effect
is that in order to
set the range from our scenario
we’ve had to make it a configurable property
of the system
So if our business stakeholders ever
change their minds about the range
we won’t have to go hunting around in the code
for where we’d hard-coded it
Notice how the steps that create
the three people are very similar
When we see steps like this
Gherkin’s Given When Then syntax
starts to feel a bit clunky
Imagine if we could just
write out a table like this
Well, we’re in luck. You can!
Gherkin has a special syntax
called Data Tables
that allows you to specify
tabular data for a step
using pipe characters to mark the
boundary between cells
As you can see, the step definition
implicitly takes a single argument
which as this comment explains is a
Cucumber::Ast::DataTable
This object has a rich API for using
the tabular data
At its most basic, the table is just a
two-dimensional array of arrays
You don’t have to use a
column header row in a data table
but when you do, you can ask for just the data
When you do use column headers
it can be useful to fetch each data row as a hash
with the column names as keys
and the values from the cells in that row
Now we can easily iterate over these hashes
and turn them into instances of Person
With that done, we can delete our
old step definition, which is now unused
Cucumber strips all the white space
surrounding each cell
so we can have a nice neat table in the Gherkin
but still get clean values
in the step definition underneath
Notice we’ve still had to convert the location
from a string to an integer
because Cucumber can’t know that’s the
type of value in our table
You can also use the map_column method for this
The new table’s location column will now contain
integers rather than the raw strings
Now the way we’ve specified this data is OK
but it’s quite hard to visualise
where each of the people is stood
It might be better to express it like this instead
Do you like that better?
You do, but you’re worried how
we’ll handle it in our step definition?
Fear not. Cucumber has you covered
The Data Table has a transpose method
which returns a new DataTable
where each row is turned into a column
Now we can use the transposed table object
as we did before
Let’s tidy up this code so as not to keep
using all these temporary variables
Data tables are very useful for
setting up data in Given steps
but you can also use them for specifying outcomes
One rule that we’ve been implying but have
never actually explored with an example
is that people remember everything they’ve heard
So far we’ve only specified a single message
so let’s try writing a scenario
where Sean shouts more than once
See how natural it is to use a Data Table here?
We also haven’t used any column headers in this case
since the data is all in a single column anyway
So how do we implement this step definition?
Well, the DataTable has
a really handy method called diff!
that we can use to compare two Data Tables
diff! will pass if the tables are the same
and fail if they’re different
So we need the actual messages
that Lucy’s heard
to be stored in an object that looks like a DataTable
so we can compare it to the ones we expect
A two-dimensional Array will do
so we can just map over Lucy’s messages and create
a new single-item Array for each row
Now we can pass that two-dimensional Array
to the diff method
on the table of expected messages
passed in from the Gherkin
Oops! It looks like we made a typo in our scenario
We should have included exclamation marks
on the expected messages
Well, at least this gives you a chance to see
the nice diff output from Cucumber
when the tables are different
We see the expected values in orange
and the actual values in white
Let’s fix just one of these so you can see how
the diff output changes
The matching bagels! line is green
and for the mismatched row
the actual output is white
and the expected output is orange
Let’s fix that last typo
and we should be green again
Great
When writing scenarios, occasionally we want
to use a really long piece of data
For example, let’s introduce a new rule
about the maximum length of a message
...and add a scenario to illustrate it
making the string just over
the boundary of the rule
That’s pretty ugly isn’t it!
Still, we’ll press on and get it to green
then we’ll show you how to clean it up
Our existing step definition handles that
ugly step with the long message just fine
but we need a new step definition
for this last outcome step
We’ll iterate over all the people in the scenario
and check they haven’t heard this message
OK, so we have a failing acceptance test
Let’s dive down into our solution
and implement this new rule
It seems like the Network should be
responsible for implementing this rule
so let’s go to its unit tests and add a new
example to specify this extra responsibility
We’ll create a 181-character message like this...
place Lucy and Sean in their usual positions
subscribe Lucy on the network
and then assert that Lucy should not hear
the message when it’s broadcast
Let's run that test
Good, it fails
Lucy’s still getting the message at the moment
Now how are we going to implement this?
It looks like we’re already implementing the
proximity rule here in the broadcast method
Let’s add another if statement here
about the message length
Run the unit test again...
and it’s passing. Great
The code here has got
a little bit messy and hard to read
One very basic move we could make to improve it
would be to just extract
a couple of temporary variables
That's better
This code could be improved even further of course
but at least we haven’t made it any worse
Let’s just run the tests to check
Great - everything’s still green
Now we have everything passing again
we can tidy up the Gherkin to use
a new piece of syntax
we’ve been wanting
to tell you about:
a DocString
DocStrings allow you to specify a text argument
for a step that spans over multiple lines
We could change our step to look like this instead
Now the scenario is much more readable
We don’t use DocStrings very often -
having such a lot of data in a test
can often make it quite brittle
But when you do need it
it's useful to know about
You might have noticed
that we’ve followed a pattern
when we added behaviour to the system
during this episode
First we expressed the behaviour
we wanted in a Gherkin scenario
wired up the step definitions
then ran Cucumber to watch it fail
Then, we found the first class in our
domain model that needed to change
in order to support that new behaviour
In this case, the Network class
We used a unit test to describe how
we wanted instances of that class to behave
Then we ran the unit test and watched it fail
We focused in and made changes to the class
until its unit tests were passing
When the unit tests were passing
we then made some minor changes to
clean up the code and make it more readable
This is the basic test-driven-development cycle:
red
green
clean
The technical name for this
last clean-up step is refactoring
Refactoring is an ugly name for
an extremely valuable activity:
improving the design of existing code
without changing its behaviour
You can think about it like cleaning up
and washing the dishes after
you’ve prepared a meal:
basic housekeeping
But imagine the state of your kitchen
if you never made time to do the dishes
Go on, imagine it for a second
Yuck!
Well, that’s how many, many codebases end up
The good thing about taking this course
is that we’re teaching you how
to write solid automated tests
and the good thing about having
solid automated tests
is you can refactor with confidence
knowing that if you accidentally change the system’s behaviour
your tests will tell you
Once we’re done refactoring
what do we do next?
Run Cucumber, of course!
In this case, our scenario was passing with
a single trip round the inner TDD loop
but sometimes you can spend several hours
working through all the unit tests
you need to get a single scenario to green
Once the acceptance test is passing
we figure out the next
most valuable scenario on our todo list
and start the whole thing all over again!
Together, these two loops make the BDD cycle
The outer loop,
which starts with an acceptance test
keeps us focused on what the business
needs us to do next
The inner loop
where we continuously test
implement, then refactor
small units of code
is where decide how
we’ll implement that behaviour
Both of these levels of feedback are important
It’s sometimes said that your acceptance tests
ensure you’re building the right thing
and your unit tests
ensure you’re building the thing right
That’s all for this lesson of Cucumber School
See you next time!
Captions created by Jayson Smith for Cucumber Ltd.