Hello and welcome to the second lesson
here at Cucumber School
Last time we learned how to use
conversations about concrete examples
to explore your problem domain
and decide what to build
In this episode you'll learn how to
describe those examples using the
Gherkin specification language
so that Cucumber can run them
Then, we'll drive out a solution using
a failing Cucumber scenario to guide us
There's going to be a fair amount
of programming in this episode
and some object-oriented design as well
We want this to feel real
so we'll work on something fun
A social networking application!
Shouty is a social network that allows
people who are physically close to communicate
just like people have always communicated
with their voices
In the real world you can talk to someone
in the same room or across the street
or even a hundred metres
away from you in a park
if you shout
That's Shouty!
What you say in this social network
can only be heard by people who are nearby
Let's start with a very basic example
of Shouty's behaviour
Something we might have discussed
in a Three Amigos meeting
Sean the shouter shouts
"Free bagels at Sean's!"
And Lucy the listener
who happens to be stood across the street
from his store 15 metres away, hears him
She walks into Sean's coffee shop
and takes advantage of the offer
We can translate this into a Gherkin scenario
so that Cucumber can run it
Here's how that would look
You can see that there are four
special keywords being used here
Scenario just tells Cucumber we're about
to describe an example that it can execute
Then you see the lines beginning with
Given, When, and Then
Given is the context for the scenario
We're putting the system into a specific state
ready for the scenario to unfold
When is the action
Something that happens to the system that will
cause something else to happen: an outcome
Then is the outcome
It's the behaviour we expect from the system
when this action happens in this context
You'll notice we've omitted from our outcome
anything about Lucy
walking into Sean's store and making a purchase
Remember, Gherkin is supposed to
describe the behaviour of the system
so it would be distracting to have
that detail in our scenario
Each scenario has these three ingredients:
a context, an action, and one or more outcomes
Together, they describe one single aspect
of the behaviour of the system
Now that we've translated our
example into Gherkin
we can automate it
The easiest way to get started
with Cucumber for Java is to
use a template project with a build script
that sets everything up correctly
You can download this template project from GitHub
Open your web browser and go to the
'cucumber-java-skeleton' project on GitHub
If you're comfortable with git
you can just clone the project
If you're new to git, don't worry
we'll download a zip file instead
Click releases and download the
most recent that file that starts with a v
If you're on Windows
click the zip file to download it
If you're on OSX or Linux
just copy the link and download it with wget
On Windows, extract the zip file
by double-clicking on it or
if you're on OSX or Linux
extract it with the unzip command
After extracting the zip file
we'll rename the directory to 'shouty'
In your shell, 'cd' into the shouty directory
The template project contains
Maven and Ant build scripts
that makes it easier to get started
with Cucumber for Java
We'll be using Maven
so if you haven't installed that already
now is a good time
Let's take a look at what else is in this project
There is a main directory for our application code
and a test directory for our test code
Let's remove some of the files
that come with the project
Remove Belly.java, Stepdefs.java, and Belly.feature
Now we have a bare bones project
We'll be building it from the ground up
so you can see what is going on
Before we open the project in our IDE
we're going to modify the name of the application
We'll use a text editor for this
I'm using the Atom editor
but you can use anything you like
Open pom.xml and change the
groupId, artifactId, and name
We're ready to start coding!
We're going to use
IntelliJ IDEA Community Edition
because it has really nice
Cucumber integration built in
If you prefer to use a different IDE
such as Eclipse, that's fine too.
To open the project in IntelliJ
just open the pom.xml file
Let's rename the package
from skeleton to Shouty
In IntelliJ you can rename it
via the Refactor menu
The first file we're going to create
is a feature file
where we will write our first scenario
Create a file called shout.feature
in the shouty directory, under resources
Now that we have a scenario it's time to run it!
Switch back to the command prompt
and run 'mvn clean test'
Maven will now download Cucumber
compile your code
and tell Cucumber to run the feature file
You'll see that Cucumber has found
our feature file and read it back to us
We can see a summary of the results at the bottom
Three steps, one scenario, all undefined
Let's run the scenario again
from inside IntelliJ
Select the feature file and choose run
from the context menu
This will give you similar output
Undefined means Cucumber doesn't know
what to do for any of the three steps
we wrote in our Gherkin scenario
It needs us to provide some step definitions
Step definitions translate
from the plain language
you use in Gherkin, into code
When Cucumber runs a step
it looks for a step definition
that matches the text in the step
If it finds one, then it
executes the code in the step definition
If it doesn't find one
well, you've just seen what happens
Cucumber helpfully prints out
some code snippets that we can use
as a basis for new step definitions
Let's copy those
We'll create a new class in the shouty package
where we'll paste those snippets
Make sure you create it under test and not main
Now IntelliJ's complaining that
there are some unknown symbols
We need to add some import statements
Pressing alt-enter will do that for us
Let's return to the scenario and run it again
There is a small bug in IntelliJ's
Cucumber integration
Sometimes it doesn't tell Cucumber
where to find step definitions
This is easy to work around
Just edit the Run configuration
and make sure the Glue field
contains the value of your package
Now run Cucumber again
This time the output is a little different
We now have a pending step
and two skipped ones
This means Cucumber found all our
step definitions and executed the first one
But that first step definition
throws a Pending exception
which causes Cucumber to stop
skip the rest of the steps
and mark the scenario as pending
It's time to work on our solution
At this point we need to do
a little domain modeling
The words in the step
provide us some good hints
about some names that
will appear in our domain model
Our scenario mentions
two people Lucy and Sean
so it looks like we'll need
a couple of person objects at least
Each person will also need to
know their own location
Cucumber is telling us to
write the code we wish we had
Let's do it!
To implement this step we need to create
a couple of person objects
with a specified distance between them
We could write it like this
Start by renaming the 'arg1' parameter
to something that better reflects its meaning
We'll call it distance
To keep things simple
we're going to assume
all people are situated on a line
A one-dimensional coordinate system
We can always introduce proper geo locations later
We'll place Sean in the center
and Lucy 15 metres away from Sean
Notice that the number 15
does not appear anywhere in our code
The value 15 is automatically passed
from the Gherkin step into the step definition
If you're curious
that's the '\d' in the
pattern of the step definition
We'll explain regular expressions
in detail in a future lesson
Before we can run the code we just wrote
we need to fix the compilation errors
Let's create a class called person
Then we'll add a setter for the location
When we run the scenario again
the first step is green!
We'll follow the same flow
to make the remaining two steps pass
do a little bit of domain modeling
write the code we wish we had
make it compile, and run the scenario
In the second step definition
we want to tell Sean to shout something
In order to send instructions to Sean
we need to store him in an instance variable
so that he'll be accessible
from all of our definitions, like this
Our Person class needs a 'shout' method
Let's add it!
Don't worry about the implementation yet
The important thing right now is to
discover the shape of our domain model
The last step definition is where
we implement the check or assertion
We'll verify that what Lucy has heard
is exactly the same as what Sean shouted
Once again we're going to
write the code we wish we had
So we need a way to ask Lucy
what messages she's heard
and we also need to know
what it was that Sean shouted
We can record what Sean shouts
by storing it an instance variable
as the When step runs
This is a common pattern to use
in Cucumber step definitions
when you don't want to repeat
the same test data in different
parts of a scenario
Now we can use that value
in the assertion check
We also need to add a getMessagesHeard
method to our Person class
Let's do that now
This is great!
Whenever we do BDD, getting to our
first failing test is a milestone
Seeing the test fail, proves that it is
capable of detecting errors in our code
Never trust an automated test
that you haven't seen fail!
Now all we have to do is write
the code to make it pass
That's the easy bit!
In this case we're going to cheat
We have a one line fix that will
make the scenario pass
It's not a particularly...
future-proof implementation
Can you guess what it is?
I'll show you
Hmm, there. I told you it
wasn't very future-proof!
Still, the fact that such a poor
implementation can pass our tests
shows us that we need to work on our tests
A more comprehensive set of scenarios would
force us to write a better implementation
This is the essence of
behaviour-driven development
Examples of behaviour drive the development
So we know we need more scenarios
and a better solution
Instead of writing a note on our TODO list
let's write another failing scenario
Now when we come back to this code
we can just run the tests
and Cucumber will remind us
what we need to do next
We're done for the day!
Go make yourself a cup of tea
Captions created by Jayson Smith for Cucumber Ltd.