BDD stands for Behaviour Driven Development
But what does that mean?
What does it mean to do BDD?
Well BDD is a process of exploring
discovering, defining,
and then finally driving out the
desired behaviour of a software system
using conversations
concrete examples
and automated-tests
We use conversations about concrete
examples to explore, discover,
and finally illustrate our
shared understanding
of the problem we need to solve
for our stakeholders
Then we refine those examples into
automated-tests that describe the
desired behaviour of our solution
to drive the development of the system
Cucumber is a tool facilitates BDD
We can't teach you about Cucumber without
teaching you about BDD, too
so that's what we're going to start
Let's start by defining what we mean
by a concrete example
Can you think of a concrete example of
the last time you used a piece of software?
Maybe an app you often use
on your smartphone
or something you use on a daily basis
on your desktop computer
Write down your example
Now, I've got no way to tell from
here inside this video
but I'd be willing to bet you didn't give me
a concrete example of you
using the software
You just wrote down the name of
the program or the app you were using
For example, maybe you wrote down
Twitter
Let's try again
Give me a concrete example of the
last time you used Twitter
or whatever the app was you had in mind
Ready? Go!
Let's see
Did you just write down a
concrete example with details of
what you were trying to do at the time
and why you used the app?
Or did you just write down
the name of the feature
like..
read my messages on Twitter?
This is still too abstract
Getting concrete is hard!
If you just wrote down the name of the
feature I want you to try again
Visualise a real moment in your life
when you use that feature
Tell me about it in every last detail
Here's my example
Yesterday I was waiting for my
regular train home from work
I have a half hour commute so I like to
have something to read on the train
Because the train goes to a rural area
where the mobile signal is bad
I scanned my Twitter feed and
fired up a browser tab
with interesting looking articles
to read before I get on the train
Most of the articles are about
software development
but there were a couple
about politics, too
Now we're talking!
We have a concrete example with
loads of context
That really gives us something
to work with
Now we're going to see how we use
these concrete examples in practice
A prerequisite for doing BDD
is to have an agile process in place
BBD needs to be done just in time
at the last responsible moment
because we place a lot of emphasis
on conversations rather than trying to
write everything down
If you try to have those conversations
too far ahead of doing the work
you'll have forgotten most of
what you talked about
So you need to have your work already
broken down into user stories
Ideally, you'll have also started to
define acceptance criteria
or business rules for those stories
But they don't need
to be exhaustive yet
we'll flesh them out during
the BBD process
Let's imagine we're building a
point-of-sale system for an electronics retailer
Dixies
Here's our next user story!
Process Refunds
In order to satisfy
customers statutory rights
As a sales assistant
I need to be able to process refunds
In order to prepare this story for
development we have what we call
a three amigos meeting
We call it the three amigos
because it involves
three different disciplines from the team
Test
Development
and Product
Let's watch one in action
The business rules to this story
are really simple
Any item can be returned within 14 days
as long as the customer has a receipt
Can you give me an example?
Okay
Collin the customer bought
a kettle last week from us
When he got home he realised the colour
didn't match his kitchen cabinets
and he really didn't like it
Um, he's brought it back to
the store for refund
He walks up to Sally
a junior sales assistant
and he asks her to process the refund
What's the outcome here?
What are we supposed to test?
Well we need to increment the
stock quantity for that item
so we know it's back in our inventory
Ah right, anything else?
No, no, I think that's all
What if Collin doesn't have his receipt?
Does Sally have to send him home?
Well, a manager can process a refund
with any proof of purchase
Collin could use a bank statement
for example?
But Sally can't do that so
she would have to ask her boss
Right, so there are two rules here:
The customer must have
proof of purchase, not just a receipt
and if they don't have their receipt
then it must be authorized
by a manager, right?
Oh, oh right! Exactly!
Aren't we forgetting something here?
Isn't Collin supposed to get his money back?
Oh! Uh, oh yes of course!
And does the system need to notify
anyone in the warehouse to
come pick up the kettle?
Good idea, Tammy.
Yes, I think that's out of our scope
for this version of the story
but I'll put it on the
backlog for future iteration
As you can see
the three amigos meeting
raises lots of questions
It's a really useful way to discover
assumptions and potential misunderstandings
It is also a great way to communicate
requirements that somebody
might have thought about
but never explained clearly to
other people on the team
Sometimes the three amigos will hit
a question that nobody in the room
knows the answer to
These are also a valuable output
from the meeting
Now you have a clear picture
of what you know and
what you need to find out
Talking through examples
is a great way
to get everyone on the same page
about what needs to be built
Once all three amigos are happy
that they understand the story
then you can start translating your examples
into something that Cucumber can understand
Here's one of our examples
written out in Gherkin
the specification language for Cucumber
As you can see
Gherkin's almost like plain English
We have to use a few special key words so that Cucumber can understand it, too
Words like feature, scenario,
given, when, and then
You'll learn all about these soon
We can refine as many examples
as we need into this form
to create an executable specification
for our software
In the next lesson
you'll learn how to create
your first Cucumber scenario
and execute it
Captions created by Jayson Smith for Cucumber Ltd.