Last time on Cucumber School
we showed you how to use
example mapping
to facilitate conversations between stakeholders
before starting work on a new user story
We finished the lesson on a technical note
showing you how to extract
a layer of support code from your
step definitions
to keep your Cucumber code easy -
and cost-effective - to maintain
We’re going to keep things technical
in this lesson
Remember that bug we spotted right back at
the beginning of lesson seven
where our user was over-charged
if they mentioned “buy”
several times in the same message?
It's time to finally knuckle down and fix it
As we do so, you’re going to get
some more experience
of the inner and outer TDD loops that
we first introduced you to in lesson five
We’ll learn about mock objects
and explore the difference between
unit tests and acceptance tests
and learn the value of each
If you’re someone who doesn’t normally
dive deep into code, try not to worry
We’ll keep the example from moving too fast
and we hope you’ll find it educational
to see how different kinds of tests
complement each other
in helping you build a quality product
Let’s work outside-in and start by
tidying up the Gherkin specification
Right now, the scenario is still in the raw form
it was in when the bug was first reported
with a name that references an ID
in our bug tracking system
This doesn’t make for very good documentation
about the intended behaviour
Using our Friends episode naming convention
that we introduced in lesson 7
we can come up with a more expressive name
for this scenario
How about:
the one where Sean mentions “buy”
several times in the same shout?
You might be worried about losing this bug ID
We could keep it
in a comment, a tag, or in the description
of the Scenario if we wanted to
If your team likes to keep track of such things
feel free to do that
We’d prefer to consign the bug to history -
what matters to us
is how the software behaves today
not how it got to be that way
We think the values in the example could be
changed to make it a little more expressive
If we start Sean off with 100 credits
and end him with 95
it more clearly illustrates the rule that
only five credits should be deducted
Talking of which
let’s also update the rule to make it explicit
that you lose 5 credits per shout
Good
Now let’s run our improved scenario
using the @todo tag
and go hunting for that bug
OK, well we can see our scenario is failing
but where do we need to go to fix it?
Luckily, our system is pretty small
and we remember that all the
premium account behaviour is implemented in
the Network class, so let’s go and look there
Well, that broadcast method is pretty complex
but I suppose the bug must be in there somewhere
Let’s try to pin it down with a unit test
Oh dear, oh dear:
This file does not contain any tests for
the premium account behaviour!
It looks like when that so-called
hot-shot ninja rockstar subcontractor, Stevie
hacked in the first version of premium accounts
he drove everything from that
one great big Cucumber scenario
and never wrote any unit tests
Why is this a problem?
Well, think about each automated test you write
as warning light that you’re fitting to your system
Acceptance tests are warning lights
that make sense to business people:
when they fail
they tell you what functionality a user
will not be able to enjoy because of the bug
What a unit test does is give the programmers
an indication about why the bug has occurred
Ideally, whenever you see an acceptance test’s
warning light flash
there should be at least one corresponding
unit test flashing too
pointing the developers to
the source of the problem
If you don’t have any unit tests
you’re left guessing where the problem lies
In a big system
this can be a serious waste of time
So the responsible thing to do at this point is to
retrofit some unit tests for the Network class
We’ll start with its existing behaviour
then go on to test-drive the behaviour
we need to fix our bug
Let’s write a test case for deducting five credits
when the word “buy” is mentioned once
All our existing tests use a
test double or mock object
to represent the instance of Person
that the Network collaborates with
So let’s go with that and try to do the same here
First we need a mock object to represent Sean
And we’ll need to broadcast a
message containing the word “buy”
What next?
Well we need to assert that Sean is told
to reduce his credits
In the deduct_credits method here
we’re calling the credits setter
setting it to five less than the current value
So we need to stub the attribute getter with
say 100 credits, and then check
that the setter is called with 95
Here's how we do that
This test is a real pain to write
and we’re still not done!
Now it’s failing with this error
Following the stack trace
it looks like the problem is
that our list of listeners
hasn’t been initialised
The Network class has been built with the
assumption that there’s always going to be
at least one listener subscribed
So even though it’s not relevant to our test
we’ll need to create a Lucy
and subscribe her to the Network
She’ll also need to be ready to receive a call
to hear when the message is broadcast
Phew. Our test is passing at last
That was hard work
and what we’ve produced is just awful
This ugly test is typical of what happens
when you use mock objects or test doubles
to retro-fit tests to existing code
So why use mocks?
Mock objects are a design tool
They’re intended to be used when
constructing new code
to throw together a lightweight sketch
of a collaborating object
When you’re focused on building a Network
and you think it needs to
collaborate with a Person
it would slow you down to have to
go off to build the actual Person class
It’s often quicker to use a mock object
to hash out your idea of roughly
what Person might look like
leaving you to stay focused on the task at hand
As you do this
you’ll find yourself - as we just did
having to specify how you want
the two objects to interact
If you think about it, this interaction -
the way they talk to each other at runtime -
is the true behaviour of these objects
Remember back in lesson 5, Loops
where we explained that acceptance tests
help you build the right thing
and unit tests help you build the thing right?
In other words, acceptance tests help us to
explore the problem domain
while unit tests help us explore the solution
When you drive your development from tests
the unit tests can give you feedback
about the design of your solution
If it’s easy to take an individual object and
plug it into your tests
your design is likely to be nicely modular
which means it will be easier
to change in the future
If it’s awkward, that’s a signal
there’s a problem with your design
We call this listening to the tests
One alternative to using mocks would be to
use a real instance of Person
instead of the mock object
This has a couple of apparent advantages
First, Person automatically subscribes
to the Network as it is constructed
so we wouldn’t need this clutter about Lucy
Also, because we’re testing Person and Network
as one integrated lump
we don’t have to fuss about exactly
how they communicate about Sean’s credits
All we have to do is check how many credits
he has left over at the end
But this seductive solution papers over
the cracks in our design
When you use mocks, you put the microscope on the
interaction between an object and its collaborators
This gives you feedback about
how coupled those objects are
A lot of chatter going back and forth like this
suggests they’re getting tangled up together
So the fact that it’s awkward to use mocks here
is not because mocks are bad
or because we’re bad at using mocks:
it’s feedback from the code
Let’s listen to the tests and try to respond
to this pain instead of ignoring it
We’ll start with something easy
and deal with the situation where
the Network is asked to broadcast
when it has no listeners
This is an annoying detail about
how this object behaves that didn’t
show itself in our acceptance tests
Let’s test-drive a fix
To fix it, all we need to do
is initialise the collection of listeners
in the constructor
which makes more sense anyway
Easy!
And with that fixed
we can simplify the test we just wrote
Let’s take stock a little bit
We’re trying to fix that bug about
multiple mentions of the word “buy”
but first we’re retrofitting unit tests for the
premium account behaviour in the Network class
It will be easier to see what tests are missing
if we reorganize the unit tests
by Network’s responsibilities
They basically fall into two categories
These ones here are to do with
the responsibility of broadcasting to listeners
so let’s group them up using
RSpec’s describe method
Now we have our new test
which is about charging for shouts
This last one here is a bit weird
It’s sort of about broadcasting to listeners
but it has this odd hack in it
which needs further investigation
This test is quite obscure
and seems to be attempting to cover
several aspects of
Network’s behaviour all at once
Let’s document those individual behaviours
as new tests
and we can come back
to deal with this one later
We can see we’ll need something under the
responsibility of broadcasting to listeners
to ensure long messages aren’t broadcast
for people with no credits
so we can express that using
a pending RSpec example
We can fill this out later
It’s clear we’ll also need to test that
we charge two credits for an over-long message
Let’s add another pending example for that
Once those two tests are implemented
we won’t need this obscure one any more
We’re not confident enough to just remove it
until we’ve seen those tests fleshed out
so we can mark it as pending for now
That will remind us we need to
come back and clean this up soon
At this point it is becoming clear that
Network has too many responsibilities
We have two different sources of feedback
telling us this
With the unit tests laid out by responsibility
we can see more clearly
that while broadcasting to listeners
is a responsibility that fits
there’s no real reason why the Network
needs be responsible for charging for shouts
Secondly, the communication protocol
between Network and Person
exposed by the mocks, is very noisy:
we’re making lots of method calls to Person
in order to determine whether they can
afford the shout and to deduct payment
First Sean calls Network#broadcast
then Network asks Sean how many credits he has
then Network tells Sean
the new value of his credits
with the fee for the message deducted
then Network asks Sean
how many credits he has again
in order to check whether he can afford
to send the message!
We could get all sad and angry that if only
we’d test-driven this code in the first place
we might have got this feedback sooner
but that would be futile:
it's not too late to clean this code up!
How about we make Sean responsible for
organising his own payment?
Instead of rewriting this code
let’s see if we can refactor it
When refactoring, it’s crucial not to
break existing functionality
so we’ll rely on our tests to warn us
if we make a mistake
We’ll work in small steps
We may temporarily break some unit tests
as the implementation shifts
but the acceptance tests should be
passing all the way through
if everything goes according to plan
Ready?
We’ll start by moving the
deduct_credits method onto Person
As a baby-step, we’ll make it public
so we can just continue to call it
from Network’s broadcast method for now
That should keep the acceptance tests passing
Good
Now let’s make Sean responsible for
deducting his own credits, as he shouts
We can move over this whole responsibility
of charging for shouts
from the network specs
to the person specs
We’ll need to adjust the test like this...
and we’re back to green!
Let’s refactor some more
Because all this code is running
within the shouter object now
we don’t need to pass around this
instance of Person anymore
and we can access the
credits instance variable here, directly
We can make deduct credits private now
We don’t need to pass short enough
around as a variable...
we can just do the logic inline here
Great, now the code in Network#broadcast
is much cleaner
We still have these pending unit tests
we need to sort out
Let’s start in Person, by fleshing out
this test about charging for long messages
That's better
Let’s just make it fail quickly
to check that we can trust it
Okay
now we can tackle these two
ignored unit tests in Network
Let’s step back for a second
and consider the rule we’re implementing here
This original unit test was simply there
to ensure that long messages were not broadcast:
remember we originally started out
without premium accounts
With the addition of premium accounts
the rule has changed:
We will broadcast long messages
but only if the person shouting
has sufficient credits
To implement it, we’ve ended up with
this mind-bending boolean logic
in the broadcast method
It doesn’t have to be like this
This complexity is a sign that
we haven’t modelled the problem well enough yet
Recall that right at the end of lesson 7
we discovered a
known unknown in our problem domain
and documented it with this question:
what happens when you run out of credits?
We know you can’t send a long message when
you run out of credits
but what about a message
containing the word ‘buy’?
Perhaps having a complete answer to this question
will help us to resolve this complexity
Let’s check with our product owner
We use a scenario to frame the discussion
with Paula, our product owner
Given Lucy and Sean are
within range of each other -
that’s what these background steps do -
and Sean has bought 4 credits...
when Sean shouts a message
containing the word “buy” then…
then what?
Sean doesn’t have enough credits
so presumably Lucy does not hear his message
is that right?
Right, says Paula
And so in that case, Sean should
still have his four credits, correct?
Right again, says Paula
OK, thanks Paula
So the rule is that we’ll only
send shouts that you can afford
Is that right?
Correct! says Paula.
A person can’t send a premium shout
unless they have enough credits to pay for it
Now we understand the business rule
let’s automate this scenario
and drive out the behaviour
First we need to match this new step
where we check Lucy does not hear Sean’s message
We have a very similar one here for Larry
We can use a capture group to make it more generic
Instead of a wildcard though
we can use pipes to specify
the alternative values we expect here
We capture the listener name
then use that here
when fetching the instance of Person
Right, now we have a failing acceptance test
which should be passing once we’ve resolved this
Let’s have a think about where
this behaviour should go
If we give the responsibility for checking
affordability to the Person doing the shouting
then Network doesn’t need to
care about credits at all
which will simplify things nicely
Let’s start with a new unit test for Person then
We’ll set up Sean with only one credit
not enough to afford to send a long message -
and assert that the broadcast method
is not called on Network
Then we try to shout the long message
This fails of course, because at the moment
Person doesn’t make this check
so the broadcast method is called every time
We’re at Red in the TDD cycle
Next stop: green!
To make this pass we need to know
how much the shout is going to cost
before we send it
That knowledge is currently
in the deduct_credits method
which actually does
two tasks at the same time:
it works out the cost of the message, and
it deducts that cost from the person’s balance
Let’s tease those two tasks apart
first calculating the cost of the shout
then deducting that cost from the credits
Now we can extract a method that calculates
the cost of the message
Then finally we can use that method
to check whether the message is affordable
and our unit test is passing
Great!
And I suppose our acceptance test for
the affordability rule should be passing now too
It is!
We’re green, so it’s refactoring time again!
Now we can give that messy old test in
Network’s unit tests the treatment it deserves
because this behaviour is now on Person
We won’t be needing this pending test
and we don’t need to stub credits here anymore
Deleting code is my favourite
kind of refactoring!
Let’s keep going and strip back all that
crazy boolean logic in Network#broadcast
I think we can just remove this whole clause
about the message being too short
or having enough credits or whatever
Let’s try it and see what the tests tell us
Excellent, much better!
Now, can we do any refactoring in Network?
Well this method would read a lot better if
we extract a method that returns only
the listeners within range of the shouter
Let’s do that
We don’t need to use this shouter_location
temporary variable either
Let’s just inline it
OK. The code is nice and clean
and all our tests are passing...
except for one:
that bug!
It can’t escape us any longer.
Let's trap it with a unit test
We know the responsibility for charging
for shouts lies in Person
so that’s where to add the unit test
Have you already spotted
where we need to make the change?
Here, in the cost_of method
the code will add five credits to the cost
each time it finds the word “buy” in the message
If we change the code like this
it should be working as expected
It is!
Great stuff
Although we’ve called this
video series Cucumber School
you’ve probably noticed by now
that we’re teaching you
a whole range of skills and ideas that
we on the Cucumber team use to develop software
Not just skills with Cucumber
but skills with the whole of
Behaviour-Driven Development
BDD blurs the lines between traditional roles
like tester and developer
In our ideal world
everyone on the team - not just testers -
is responsible for quality, and we all
try to test it as much as possible
Having good automated tests
frees up testers to do more
interesting, interactive, exploratory testing
We use our tests as a guide to help us
design a solution that models the problem well
A better model in your solution can
make a whole category of bugs go away forever
We saw that in this lesson
when we moved the responsibility
for charging for shouts from Network to Person
and the issues around what happened when you run
out of credit suddenly became easy to resolve
Getting the right balance between
fine-grained unit tests and
broader full-stack tests
is critically important to having fast
useful feedback from your test suite
We’ll explore this more in the next lesson
See you next time, on Cucumber School
Captions created by Jayson Smith for Cucumber Ltd.